<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A diuine enthymeme of true obedience: or, A taske for a Christian. Preached at Pauls Crosse the tenth of September, 1615. by Anthonie Hugget Maister of Arts, and parson of the Cliffe neare Lewis in Sussex</title>
            <author>Hugget, Anthony.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1615</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 173 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 39 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A03790</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 13909</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S116568</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99851784</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99851784</idno>
            <idno type="VID">17075</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A03790)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 17075)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1312:04)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A diuine enthymeme of true obedience: or, A taske for a Christian. Preached at Pauls Crosse the tenth of September, 1615. by Anthonie Hugget Maister of Arts, and parson of the Cliffe neare Lewis in Sussex</title>
                  <author>Hugget, Anthony.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 71, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Richard Field for Francis Faulkner, and are to be sold at his shop in new Fish-street, vnder Saint Margarets Church,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1615.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-02</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-04</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-06</date>
            <label>Judith Siefring</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-06</date>
            <label>Judith Siefring</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:17075:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A DIVINE EN<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>THYMEME OF TRVE OBEDIENCE: <hi>OR, A Taske for a
Chriſtian.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Preached at Pauls Croſſe the tenth of Sep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tember, 1615. by
ANTHONIE HVGGET Maiſter of Arts, and Parſon of the Cliffe neare Lewis in
Suſſex.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Viuendo morimur, &amp; monendo viuimus.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Text. 
<q>
                  <hi>Seeing we haue theſe promiſes, dearely beloued, let vs
cleanſe our ſelues from all filthineſſe of the fleſh and ſpirit,
and grow up to full holineſſe in the feare of God.</hi> 
                  <bibl>2. Cor. 7.1.</bibl>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>London,</hi> Printed by <hi>Richard Field</hi> for <hi>Francis
Faulkner,</hi> and are to be ſold at his ſhop in new Fiſh-ſtreet, vnder
Saint Margarets Church. 1615.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:17075:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:17075:2"/>
            <head>TO THE RIGHT HONORABLE, AND MY VERY GOOD LORD, WILLIAM, Lord
Howard, Baron of Effingham, <hi>increaſe of all true honour and
happineſſe, &amp;c.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">R</seg>Ight Honorable, the im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunitie of ſome good Chriſtians
that heard this Sermon at the Croſſe, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing ouercome mee to publiſh it
to the world; I haue preſumed (vnworthy though it be) to preſent your
Lordſhip with it: as being the beſt meanes I had to manifeſt my dutie,
and how much I honour your Lordſhip: your zeale to true religion, your
honorable re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect and loue ſhewed to ſchollers, and to me in particular,
your vnworthy Chaplaine, makes me hope it ſhall find a fauourable
ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptation. The which if it ſhall pleaſe your <pb facs="tcp:17075:3"/>Lordſhip to
grant, I haue a condigne coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpoiſe of all my labour. Thus in all
hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bleneſſe crauing pardon for my boldneſſe, with my dayly
ſupplications, that God would multiplie vpon you all temporall bleſſings
in this life, and eternall in the life to come, I reſt</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Your Honours moſt dutifull and deuoted
Chaplaine</hi> ANTHONIE HVGGET.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:17075:3"/>
            <head>A DIVINE EN<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>THYMEME OF TRVE OBEDIENCE.</head>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>2. COR. 7.1.</hi>
               </bibl> 
               <p>Seeing we haue theſe promiſes (dearely beloued) let vs
cleanſe our ſelues from all filthineſſe of the fleſh and ſpirit,
and grow vp vnto full holineſſe in the feare of God.</p>
            </q>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HE proeme of Moralitie, holds good in Diuinitie,
<gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, &amp;c.<note place="margin">Ariſtot. Eth. l. 1. c.
1.</note>
               <hi>omne appetit bonum,</hi> and it is a ſure axiome: <hi>Finis
&amp; bonum conuertun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur,</hi> that vaſte Vniuerſall, like that confuſed
Chaos in the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning,<note place="margin">Gen. 1.2.</note>out of whoſe wombe
were firſt drawn all things which were made; each particular, with the whole
it ſelfe, (<gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>) do endeuour their end, as the ſmoake
flieth vpward; which truth is well ſeene in the great bodie of nature,<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> and the little bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die of man, which is
a compendium of all this All. And hath not mortall man his ſupernaturall end,
where his ſoule, a ſtranger here, may ſtay it ſelfe for euer? Yes
ſure he hath, and the end is the accompliſhment of Gods pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes; for by
faith we ſtand, and receiue in hope:<note place="margin">1. Ioh. 3.2.</note>
               <hi>Now are <pb n="2" facs="tcp:17075:4"/>we the ſonnes of God, but it doth not appeare
what we ſhall be, &amp;c.</hi> The Apoſtle therefore in the precedent
Chapter ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing earneſtly warned his Corinthians to flee the ſocie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie and
pollutions of Idolaters, as being themſelues tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples of the holy Ghoſt; in
the two laſt verſes, he ſetteth downe the ſcope and ſumme of mans
bliſſefull end, the full period of all their deſites, euen the ſweete
and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortable promiſes of God in Chriſt Ieſus, as namely ver. 16.
<hi>I will dwell in them,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Leuit.
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>.12.</note> 
               <hi>and walke in them:
and I will be their God, and they ſhall be my people.</hi> And againe ver.
17, &amp; 18. <hi>I will re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue you,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iſa 32.1. Ier.
31.1.</note> 
               <hi>and wil be a father vnto you, and you ſhall be my ſonnes
and daughters, ſaith the Lord Almightie.</hi> Now vpon the conſideration of
theſe premiſed promiſes promiſes, he inferreth and inforceth that
ſanctitie whereof my text doth treate: <hi>See<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing we haue theſe promiſes
(dearely beloued) let vs cleanſe, &amp;c.</hi> Which words containe in them
an exhortation, not barely and ſimply propounded, but ſyllogiſtically and
perſwa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiuely inforced, and may very well be called <hi>A diuine En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thymeme
of true obedience.</hi> The Antecedent part whereof is the Foundation, and the
conſequence is the Building; or if you will, the roote and growth of
godlineſſe. The Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle thus layeth the caſe: <hi>Seeing we haue
theſe promiſes, dear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly beloued;</hi> and makes the iſſue this, <hi>Let
vs cleanſe our ſelues from, &amp;c.</hi> Let vs begin as he doth, that we
may end as he did. He begins his ſuite vpon a ſure ground, <hi>Seeing we
haue theſe promiſes;</hi> and followes the cauſe for our welfare, <hi>Let
vs cleanſe our ſelues from, &amp;c.]</hi> Thus who ſo begins and ends his
dayes, ſhall die the death of the righteous, and his laſt end
ſhall be like vnto his.</p>
            <p>Turne backe your eyes once more vpon the words, and you ſhall
find in them a grounded motiue to holineſſe: in which obſerue the matter,
the maner, and both are Euan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gelical. 1. <hi>Modus compellendi (dearly beloued)
vox verè apoſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lica,</hi> iſſuing from no other lips but ſuch
as had bin touched from the Altar of the high God with the hote burning coales
of zeale and loue,<note place="margin">Iſa. 6.6.</note> and well beſeeming
the ſcholler <pb n="3" facs="tcp:17075:4"/>of ſuch a Lord, who both in life and death
did ſhew him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe to be the Lord of loue. 2. <hi>Cauſa vel fundamentum
competendi, viz. promiſſiones.</hi> In which maine ground of his
inforcement, he makes vs ioynt purchaſers with himſelfe, viz. <hi>Nos
habemus:</hi> and that of an inheritance which ſhall ſtand for euer, viz.
<hi>has promiſſiones. Promiſſiones:</hi> that is the maine thing.
<hi>Obiectum,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Obiectum.</note> the ground point of this
exhorta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion: and that we may build vpon this ground, he ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth our
intereſt and iuſt claime, and that is <hi>Subiectum.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Subiectum.</note> 
               <hi>Nos habemus: We haue theſe
promiſes:</hi> and that is the Antece<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent, the ground, the reaſon, the
roote of that which fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowes; and that which followes is an exhortation to
ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceritie and ſound obedience, to integritie and perfect ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſſe.
To the perfection whereof there are two maine labours, 1. <hi>Remotio
mali:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Remotio mali.</note> 
               <hi>Let vs cleanſe our
ſelues.</hi> 2. <hi>Subſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tutio boni:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Subſtitutio
boni.</note> 
               <hi>and grow vp, &amp;c.</hi> For the former, that we may take our
worke with vs, let vs remember the paſſages: <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> 1. <hi>Let
vs cleanſe,</hi> that is the propertie of the worke. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> 2.
<hi>Our ſelues,</hi> that is the proprietie of the perſon.
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> 3. <hi>From filthi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe,</hi> that is the matter to be
wrought vpon. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> 4. <hi>All filthi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe,</hi> there is the
generalitie of the taske. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="5"/> 5. <hi>Of the fleſh and
ſpirit,</hi> there is the ſpecialitie of the parts and powers
in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fected.</p>
            <p>Hitherto my text hath brought vs downeward, the way and path of
the death of the righteous;<note place="margin">Mortificatio.</note> wherein we
muſt crucifie the old man, not leaue one hoofe behind, not one ſinne
vnſearched. <hi>Mortifie therefore your earthly members, &amp;c.</hi>
Coloſ. 3.5. The Apoſtle tels vs, that he which aſcended, is he which
deſcended firſt;<note place="margin">Epheſ. 4.9.</note> and as I haue
de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcended with you to the ſimilitude of his death, ſo muſt you be
ingrafted to the ſimilitude of his reſurrection.<note place="margin">Rom.
6.5.</note> For you muſt riſe againe the hill of holineſſe; when we are
rooted in humilitie, we muſt riſe and ſpring:<note place="margin">Subſtitutio boni.</note> ſo the text faith, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/>
               <hi>Let vs grow vp:</hi> yea and flouriſh in the courts of our
God,<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> 
               <hi>to full holineſſe:</hi> &amp; that we may
ſtand faſt in this eſtate, we muſt take the ſtaffe of Gods feare to
prop vs vp,<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> 
               <hi>in the <pb n="4" facs="tcp:17075:5"/>feare of
God.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Reu. 20.6.</note> And this is riſing to life,
viuification: and bleſſed are they which haue part in this firſt
reſurrection.</p>
            <p>And thus hauing ſeene a ſhort view of all, the words containe
in them two generall parts: 1. The antecedent or reaſon premiſed: 2. The
conſequent or concluſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> inferred.</p>
            <p>The antecedent in theſe words, <hi>Seeing we haue theſe
promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, dearly beloued.</hi> The concluſion in theſe, <hi>Let vs
cleanſe our ſelues from all filt hineſſe of the fleſh,
&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And firſt of the former, and then of the latter; where with
tranſpoſition of the words, without alteration of the ſenſe, giue me
leaue to ſalute your patience in the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles order, <hi>Dearely
beloued.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Dearely beloued:]</hi>
               <note place="margin">Modus
com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pellendi.</note> 
               <hi>Ex abundantia cordis os loquitur:</hi> in na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture and
in Scripture you know it to be true, and here ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample and experience makes it
good in both: the Apoſtle, ſuch is the abundance of his loue, that his
tongue cannot containe, but expreſſe the feruent deſire of his heart, in
that he calleth his people, <hi>Dearly beloued.</hi> If you turne but your
thoughts to that which he faith to his Philippia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, 1.8. you ſhall find him
like the Spouſe, euen ſicke of loue to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward them: <hi>God is my record</hi>
(faith he) <hi>how greatly I long af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter you all in the bowels of Chriſt
Ieſus, &amp;c.</hi> Had the Apoſtle either receiued or expected benefite
for his loue, it had bene <hi>lex talionis;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ioh.
6.26.</note> as the multitude loued Chriſt for the loaues; and hypocrites do
euen the ſame; but for <hi>Paul</hi> to loue his Maiſters flocke for their
good, on his part gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tis, and that in the abſence of his Maiſter, this
loue is great,<note place="margin">Act. 9.15.</note> and worthy of <hi>Paul,</hi>
whom Chriſt loued, and choſe him to be the Apoſtle of the Gentiles. This
<hi>Paul,</hi> this pat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terne of loue muſt not be put vnder a buſhell, bur
ſet on a candleſticke, to giue light to all: for, this fatherly affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
is one chiefe point of the Paſtorall office. Saint <hi>Peter</hi> for the
example of all others,<note place="margin">Doct. 1.</note> is bound vpon the
allegiance of his loue to feed the flocke,<note place="margin">Ioh. 21.</note> to
ſeed them (I ſay) as a good ſhepheard with a watchfull and fatherly care
and affection. Saint <hi>Iohn,</hi> if you reade his writings, you ſhall 
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:17075:5"/>find them <hi>dulcicora melliceta,</hi> full as the Moone,
and no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but full and plentifull drops of loue, ſweeter then the honey
and the honey combe, calling them <hi>children,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. Ioh.
2.</note>
               <hi>little children, babes, little babes, beloued,</hi> and
<hi>dearely beloued. Moſes</hi> complaineth of the yoke and burden which loue
laid vpon him by conſequence of his place: for ſo you ſhal reade Numb.
11.11. <hi>Wherefore haft thou afflicted thy ſeruant, and wherefore haue I
not found fauour in thy ſight, that thou layeſt the burden of all this
people vpon me? haue I conceiued all this people? haue I begotten them, that
thou ſhouldeſt ſay vnto me, Carrie them in thy boſome, as a nurſe
beareth her ſucking child.</hi> By which we may ſee, that teachers are
<hi>paſcendo pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtores, ſed diligendo patres;</hi> paſtors for
inſtruction, but fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers for affection. For howſoeuer we muſt ſometime
come like the watchmen in the Canticles, <hi>qui non vult duci, debet
trahi;</hi> yet this ſeueritie muſt be <hi>paterna, non tyrannica; Dum das
verbera, oſtende vbera,</hi> faith <hi>Bernard:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Bern.</note> this gall muſt be mingled with honey, this bitter
water muſt come out of a ſweete fountaine; this ſharpe reprehenſion
from a lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing affection, it muſt be <hi>in ſpiritu manſuetudinis,</hi>
Galat. 6.1. <hi>Brethren, if a man be fallen by occaſion of
infirmitie, ye that are ſpirituall reſtore ſuch a one in the
ſpirit of meekneſſe.</hi> And in a word, as our voices muſt be the
voice of <hi>Iohn Baptiſt,</hi> to crie vnto them: ſo our hearts muſt be
the hearts of <hi>Paul</hi> the Apoſtle to loue them, for you are vnto vs
<hi>dearely belo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued.</hi> And are you ſo to vs, our dearely beloued?<note place="margin">Vſe.</note> Then ſo ought we to be vnto you your dearely
beloued, for if our hearts muſt be liuely fountaines running full
ſtreames of loue towards you, yours muſt not be drie ciſternes of lead to
wards vs againe: for <hi>Amor amoris mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, &amp; durus eſt qui amorem
nonrependit:</hi> Loue is the load<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtone of loue; and for the children not to
loue their fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, it is the higheſt pitch of ingratitude, a finne
againſt nature, and ſuch as is not to be named.<note place="margin">1.
Theſſ. 5.12. 1. Cor. 16.11. Gal 6.6.</note> It is the Apoſtles rule, that
you ſhould <hi>know,</hi> and that after a ſpeciall maner, <hi>thoſe
which labour amongſt you in the Lord, and haue them in <pb n="6" facs="tcp:17075:6"/>ſingular respect for their workes ſake.</hi> Surely (brethren) I
muſt ſpeake a little what I both heare and ſee to your iuſt
com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendation. It would be a notable incitement and prouo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation to all Gods
meſſengers abroad in the land, to labor diligently and conſcionably in
their callings, if their pains were but requited with ſuch loue and reſpect
as is in this Citie; if the wels of charitie which ſhould water the Eden of
God, were vnſtopped, and made to flow towards them in other places abroad, as
they do here amongſt you. That which <hi>Saba</hi> ſaid of
<hi>Solomons</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. King. 10.8.</note> ſeruants, may well
be applied to the Miniſterie of this Citie: <hi>Happie are the men, and
hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pie are thoſe thy ſeruants which ſtand euer before thee, and heare
thy wiſedome:</hi> ſo happie are thoſe Miniſters, happie are thoſe
ſeruants of God, which ſtand and ſpeake in your preſence, which waite
and miniſter at your altars. But alas, we that are criers in the
wilderneſſe, find other meaſure farre vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuting our labour of loue. If
we did raine downe euery day golden Angels into their laps, they would crie
with him, <hi>Ille mihi ſemper erit Deus, illius Aram:</hi> hugge vs, nay
adore vs, make gods of vs, bring buls dreſt with garlands to ſacrifice vnto
vs: but ſhowring downe that which is more precious then gold, and whoſe
price is farre aboue pearles, the precious comforts of the Goſpell, the
meanes of their eternall ſaluation; they are ſenſleſſe of the good we
do them. O what good bloud would it breed in vs, if as ſome other of your
ſweet ointments, good examples, I meane; ſo this of loue and kindneſſe
to them that teach you the way to heauen, might runne from the head to the
skirts of the garment, the vtmoſt coaſts and corners of the land. To
conclude this point, you that are called and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred into the place of
nurſing fathers, and you that receiue the ſincere milke of the word, that
your ſoules may grow thereby, let me exhort you in the bowels of Chriſt
Ieſus, to lend all your helping hands and conſenting hearts, that as you
haue begun, ſo you may make perfect this holy combination of
<hi>Paul</hi> and his <hi>dearely beloued. Concordia cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcunt 
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:17075:6"/>minutiſſima, diſcordia vel maxima dilabuntur.</hi>
Surely brethren, the Paſtor and the people are an holy temple, wherein the
Lord hath a delight to dwell, whoſe delight hath euer bene amongſt the
ſonnes of men: if then we wil be liuing ſtones of that holy building, it
behoueth that we be louing ſtones, ioyned together in the vnitie of the
Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit. Our life is but as a iourney to a farre more excellente. ſtate of
glorie in the kingdome of heauen, and the way thereto is but one for both, and
Saint <hi>Iames</hi> calleth it, the Kings high way of charitie, <hi>the royall
law of loue.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Via regia. lam. 2.8.</note> If there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
the Paſtor and people be Antipodes in their wayes, if they walke in
oppoſition, and harbour an antipathie of affections, and thus thinke to come
to Chriſt, they may walke from pole to pole, but ſhall neuer attaine their
end. The good ſhepheard therefore is ſaid to go before his ſheepe, and
the good ſheepe are ſaid to follow him, <hi>Ioh.</hi> 10.3. And let vs
follow the counſell of a good Paſtor to this purpoſe, <hi>Vbicertus es de
via perge mecum, vbi haeres quaere mecum:</hi> if we be both in the old and
good way,<note place="margin">Ier. 6.16.</note> let vs ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>companie and cheare one
another; but if we be wrong, let vs enquire, and guide each other. Let vs helpe
to beare one anothers burdens, and ſupply each others wants. Let the one
miniſter ſpirituall, the other carnall things. You muſt giue <hi>panem
promptuary,</hi> and we <hi>ſanctuary.</hi> We muſt receiue bread and
ſufficiencie for our liues, otherwiſe can we not giue the bread of life.
The one muſt be helpfull with the ſweate of the browes, and the other with
the ſweate and trauell of the braines. Theſe things do, and the God of
peace ſhall be with vs, <hi>God euen our God ſhall giue vs his
bleſſing: God ſhall bleſſe vs,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal.
67.6.</note> 
               <hi>and all the ends of the earth ſhall feare him.</hi> And ſo
from the maner, paſſe we to the matter.</p>
            <p>The matter in the whole and ſumme, is an exhortation to
holineſſe; but conſidered in parts and due order,<note place="margin">Fundamentû competendi.</note> we ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerued the antecedent
reaſon, and conſequent iſſue. The antecedent comes now in hand, and
offers it ſelfe vnder <pb n="8" facs="tcp:17075:7"/>theſe words, <hi>Seeing we haue
theſe promiſes.</hi> Let me pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pound it vnto you as a propoſition,
wherein obſerue, 1. <hi>Subiectum, viz. nos [We].</hi> 2. <hi>Praedicatum,
viz. promiſſiones [promiſes]:</hi> and <hi>[has habemus,]</hi> is the
<hi>copula</hi> which ioynes them together.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Subiectum</hi> doth challenge the firſt place, for it is the
firſt word.<note place="margin">1. Subiectum</note>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>We]</hi> And the parties here aimed at, are apparent,
<hi>Paul</hi> and his people, the Apoſtle and the Corinthians; the one a
choſen veſſell,<note place="margin">Act. 9.</note> of a perſecuter made a
Preacher of the name of Chriſt; the other were members of the Church of God
in Corinth,<note place="margin">2. Cor. 1.1. 2. Cor. 1.2.</note> and of the
Saints that dwelt in Achaia, thoſe that could call God their Father, and
Chriſt Ieſus their Lord; <hi>Paul</hi> and the Corinthians, beleeuers,
theſe are that <hi>(We)</hi> the ſubiect of this preſent purpoſe.</p>
            <p>All the comfortable promiſes in Chriſt Ieſus belong onely to
the faithfull.<note place="margin">Doctr.</note> So my text tels you in effect.
<hi>[We]</hi> viz. the faithfull haue theſe promiſes. Saint <hi>Paul</hi>
elſewhere makes the point more plaine, 1. Corin. 3.22. <hi>Whether ye be
Paul, or Apollos, or Cephas,</hi> (or what teacher ſoeuer may more properly
challenge you) <hi>or life, or death, whether things preſent, or things to
come, all are yours,</hi> (but not for them, nor yet for your ſelues, but
rather for this) <hi>ye are Chriſts,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Heb. 11.</note>
               <hi>and Chriſt is Gods. Abraham</hi> beleeued God a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boue hope, and is
therefore called the father of the faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full; and God makes his couenant with
him, and with his ſeed for euer, Geneſ. 17.7,8. For to the faithfull he is
rich in mercie: Exod. 20.6. he ſhewes mercie vnto thouſands in them that
beleeue in him, and loue him, &amp;c. God made his couenant with
<hi>Iſrael</hi> by name, but it was onely with the Iſrael that is of
God,<note place="margin">Rom. 9.6.</note> viz. the faithfull. <hi>For they are
not all Iſrael which are of Iſrael;</hi> but this know, <hi>that they which
are of faith, the ſame are the children of Abraha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>,</hi> Gal. 3.7. <hi>And if
you be Chriſts,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gal. 3.29.</note> 
               <hi>then are ye of
faith, then are ye Abrahams ſeed, and heires according to the promiſe. So
then, they which be of faith, are bleſſed with faithfull Abraham;</hi>
theſe haue the <pb n="9" facs="tcp:17075:7"/>promiſes. Gal. 3.9.</p>
            <p>The promiſes of Chriſt belong to the faithfull onely.<note place="margin">Reaſons.</note>
            </p>
            <p n="1">
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> 1. Becauſe they onely haue the earneſt
of the promiſes: Gal. 4.5. the adoption of ſonnes, whereby they crie,
<hi>Abba, Father,</hi> viz. the inward teſtimonie of the Spirit fealing to
their ſpirits the ocrtaintie and aſſurance of their adoption and
ſaluation in Chriſt Ieſus, Rom. 8.16.</p>
            <p n="2">
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> 2. Becauſe their names onely are written
in heauen, they are the inrolled citizens, who onely by right of proprie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie
and inheritance, haue true right, intereſt and comfort of all the ſweet
promiſes of God, either for this life or for a better; <hi>Reioyce in this
therefore, that your names are written in heauen. Luk.</hi> 10.19.</p>
            <p n="3">
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> 3. Becauſe to them onely pertaine the
couenants, as may appeare by the promulgation. viz. the word;<note place="margin">Rom. 9.4.</note> by the confirmation, viz. the Sacraments and the
oath of aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance; theſe onely belong to the faithfull, I meane in their
vertue and comfortable ends. For the word, it is to them onely the ſweet
ſauour of life vnto life, and to others it is otherwiſe, 2. Cor. 2.16. In
the Sacrament, <hi>Impy edunt cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pus Domini, ſed non corpus Dominum;</hi> in
the faithfull it hath his comfortable fruite, but in vnbeleeuers it is a ſtep
to their condemnation, 1. Cor. 11.29. And for the oath of aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurance, the
Apoſtle preciſely nameth the <hi>heires of promiſe: For God willing more
abundant to ſhew vnto the beires of pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe, the ſtableneſſe of his
couenant, hath bound himſelfe by an oath, &amp;c.</hi> Hebr. 6.17.</p>
            <p n="4">
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> 4. Becauſe that Chriſt is our
Redemption. yea our San<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctification, 1. Cor. 1.30. Our Redemption through
faith, in whoſe bloud we are reconciled to God,<note place="margin">Epheſ. 5.
Rom. 8.31. Rom. 5.8. Rom. 8.1.</note> and of enemies are made heires, Rom.
3.24. And our Sanctification alſo, in whom all the comfortable promiſes are
ſanctified to vs, and through whom all our endeuours are ſanctified and
accepted of God.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe. </seg>1</label> Do the promiſes belong to the
faithfull onely? then 1. Hence learne the freedome and libertie of Gods Saints,
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:17075:8"/>that they ſhall not be condemned with the world, Rom. 8.1.
For <hi>Now</hi> (ſaith the Apoſtle, as ſpeaking of the vertue of theſe
ſweet promiſes) <hi>there is no conde<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nation to the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> which liue godly in
Chriſt Ieſus, &amp;c.</hi> for Chriſt hath ſet the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> free, fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
ſin.<note place="margin">Reu 21.4.</note> Satan, death, hel, and condemnatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>:
but as for the wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked, it is otherwiſe, for in them ſin reigneth in their
mortal bodies, the law condemneth, the conſcience gnaweth, and accuſeth,
death executeth, the diuel rageth, and hell tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>menteth,<note place="margin">Luk.
11.26.</note>&amp; their latter end is worſe then their beginning.</p>
            <p n="2">
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> 2. Then are they not onely free from the
curſe, but alſo aſſured of the bleſſing: and this is that which
ſeaſons the bitterneſſe of all ſorrowes, though they were more bitter
then the waters of Marrah,<note place="margin">Numb. 33.8. Exod. 15.23. 2. Cor.
4.17. Auguſtine.</note> euen the promiſed <hi>eternall and farre more
excellent weight of glorie,</hi> where (as <hi>Auguſtine</hi> ſpeaketh) we
ſhall haue <hi>laetitiane ſine triſtitia, ſine dolore lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cum, ſine
labore vitam,</hi> viz. mirth without moane, place without paine, life without
labour, light without dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, where ſhall be no howling heard, nor
ſorrow knowne, but poſſeſſion of euerlaſting ioyes, <hi>ſummam
&amp; certam tranquilitatem,</hi> great tranquilitie, tranquill felicity,
happie eternitie, eternall bleſſedneſſe in the preſence of the God of
glorie, with whom is ſtabilitie and ſacietie of cuerlaſting life and
happineſſe, without danger of failing or falling, deceaſing or
decreaſing for euermore.</p>
            <p n="3">
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> 3. If theirs be the promiſes, then haue
we aſſurance of the bleſſings of this life alſo: <hi>Godlineſſe
is profit able vnto all things, which hath the promiſe of the life preſent,
and of that which is to come,</hi> 1. <hi>Tim.</hi> 4.8. So that whatſoeuer
we do (if we be within the couenant of promiſe) either concerning our bodies
or ſoules, our life preſent or our life to come, Gods bleſſing ſhall
be with vs. And therefore, ſaith <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes,</hi> Deut. 28.1, 2, 3, 4, 5.
<hi>If thou ſhalt obey diligently the voice of the Lord thy God, and
obſerue and do all his commandements, bleſſed ſhalt thou be in the
citie, and bleſſed in the field, bleſſed ſhalt thou be in the fruite
of thy bodie, and in the fruite of thy ground, the fruite of thy cattell, the
increaſe of thy kine, and the <pb n="11" facs="tcp:17075:8"/>flockes of thy ſheepe:
bleſſed ſhalt thou be when thou comeſt in, and bleſſed ſhalt thou
be when thou goeſt out: the Lord ſhall bleſſe thee in (all) that thou
ſetteſt thy hand to do,</hi> the labours of thy hands, the workes of thy
calling, yea and the medita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of thy heart. For, faith <hi>Dauid,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 1.4.</note> 
               <hi>Looke (whatſoeuer) he doth, it ſhall
prosper.</hi> So that we may with boldneſſe ſend forth our prayers, the
meſſengers of our wants, vnto the high Court of heauen, yea and be
aſſured that they ſhall be ſent back againe like the brethren of
<hi>Ioſeph,</hi> laden with the bleſſings of God. And why? we haue Gods
promiſe, that he will giue to them that aske, and open the gate to them that
knocke: this our Sauiour affirmeth, <hi>Verily, veri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly I ſay vnto you,
whatſoeuer ye ſhall aske the Father in my name, it ſhall be giuen vnto
you: aske and ye ſhall receiue, that your ioy may be full.</hi> So that of
all other comforts that can befall vs in this life, this is the greateſt,
which cannot be taken from vs, that he will heare our prayers: and though our
ſoules and conſciences be troubled with cares, and the burthen of our
ſinnes, yet he hath promiſed to caſe them. For ſo ſaith our Sauiour,
<hi>Come vnto me all ye that labour, and are heauie laden with the burden of
your ſinnes, and I will eaſe you.</hi> And though our mouthes ſhould be
ſtopped, yet well may we lift vp our ſoules to the Lord, from whence
commeth our helpe. Labour therefore to be in Chriſt, and he ſhall ſet
thee as the ſeale vpon his hand, and the ſignet on his right arme: <hi>For
the eyes of the Lord are ouer the righteous,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal.
33.18.19</note> 
               <hi>and his eares are open vnto their crie.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4">
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> 4. If the faithfull onely haue the
promiſes, then for the terrour of the wicked, for they ſhall haue no part
in theſe promiſes, but ſhall be caſt out from the preſence of God, as
<hi>Hagar</hi> and her ſonne were caſt out of the houſe of
<hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braham,</hi> Gal. 4.30. <hi>Put out the ſeruant and her ſonne, for
the ſonne of the ſeruant ſhall not be heire with the free woman.</hi>
Yea, and they ſhall not onely be depriued of the promiſe both of this life
and of a better, but ſhall ſuffer the curſe of God both of this life and
of that which is to come. <hi>The wicked <pb n="12" facs="tcp:17075:9"/>Shall be turned
into hell, and all thoſe that for get God:</hi> and, <hi>God ſhall
deſtroy the wicked for euer.</hi> And for this life, <hi>Iob</hi>
ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth, <hi>Their portion ſhall be accurſed on earth.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iob 24. 18</note> And God ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth, Deut. 28.16. <hi>If thou
ſhalt not obey and keepe all theſe my co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mandements, all theſe curſes
ſhall come vpon thee: curſed ſhalt thou be in the towne, and curſed
ſhalt thou be in the field, curſed ſhall be thy basket and thy dough, the
fruite of thy land, the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe of thy kine, and the flocks of thy
ſheepe: curſed ſhalt thou be when thou comeſt in, and curſed ſhalt
thou be when thou goeſt out.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Dcut. 28, 20.</note>
               <hi>The Lordſhall ſend curſing, trouble and ſhame in (all) that thou
ſetteſt thy hand to do.</hi> So that if thou be not in this co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenant or
promiſe of bleſſing, nothing ſhall be ſanctified from God, or
accepted to God; he will ſend curſing, trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble and ſhame in (all) thou
ſetteſt thy hand to do. Suppoſe thou performe the worke of charitie, and
giue almes; al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though it may be good to them that receiue it, yet it is a
ſinne in himſelfe: <hi>For whatſoeuer is done without faith, is
ſinne.</hi> Yea all thy goods gotten, though gotten by the ſweate of thy
browes and the labour of thy calling, yet Gods curſe remaining vpon them,
they are put in a bottomleſſe bag. For <hi>to the pure, all things are
pure, but to the impure, is nothing pure.</hi> This then is the eſtate of a
wicked man: curſed in life, curſed in death, but moſt curſed after
death, when the curſe of God ſhall torture and torment bodie and ſoule
for euer.</p>
            <p n="5">
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="5"/> 5. Hence learne the eſtate of the
faithfull to be the beſt, and the calling of a Chriſtian to be moſt
honorable. Put caſe in the moſt proſperous of the wicked, ſuch a one as
the Prophet ſpeaketh of, which neuer had knot to his death, the web of
whoſe life hath bene altogether with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out trouble or moleſtation, and let
him be compared with a ſeruant of Chriſt, which hath drunke deepe of the
cuppe of ſorrowes, and in concluſion you ſhall finde the end of this man
to be better and more glorious then his. If <hi>Alex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ander</hi> be not the
ſonne of <hi>Iupiter,</hi> his ſiluer is but droſſe, his confeſſion
ſhall be to his owne confuſion: <hi>Iam video <pb n="13" facs="tcp:17075:9"/>me
eſſe mortalem;</hi> but a true Chriſtian is the moſt honorable calling:
of the houſhold of faith,<note place="margin">Gal. 4.26. Gal. 4.5. Eph. 2.19. 1
Cor. 6.3.</note> of the ſtocke and linage of Ieruſalem aboue, by adoption
they are ſonnes, Saints by calling, kings by deputation, for the Saints
ſhall iudge the Angels, yea and reigne in the heauenly ſtate of glory for
euer. Who ſo ſaw it might ſee great difference twixt <hi>Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ues</hi> and
<hi>Lazarus</hi> while they liued; and who ſo hath not ſeene it ſhall
ſee greater diſtance twixt them now,<note place="margin">Luk. 16.19.20</note>
the one being in <hi>Abrahams</hi> boſome, the other in hell torments: where
he which formerly knew not his God nor himſelfe. nor would daigne to know
poore <hi>Lazarus,</hi> this man which once had a world at will, would now giue
a world if he had it, for one drop of cold water to coole his tong, to teach vs
that there is great differe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce twixt the rich mans <hi>non mouebor,
&amp;c.</hi> &amp; their downfall, <hi>imply deſcendunt in
infer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 30.6. Iob. 21.13.</note>O how
ſuddenly do they vaniſh, periſh, and come to a fearefull end! but as for
Gods Saints be they deſpicable in the eies of men, yet their prayers and
teares are written in the booke of Gods remembrance,<note place="margin">Eſa.
38.5.</note> and right deare and precious in the ſight of God, is the death
of all his Saints.<note place="margin">Pſal. 116.15.</note>
            </p>
            <p n="6">
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="6"/> 6. Seeing theſe promiſes for this life
and a better life re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dound to vs, &amp; to vs only: then hence let vs learne to
take comfort in theſe promiſes, in all things, whatſoeuer our dangers and
diſtreſſes are; for God euen our God, is <hi>Pater omnipotens,</hi> both
able and willing for to do vs good. Art thou then in affliction? know that
there is no darkneſſe but flieth from the Sunne, no poyſon but yeeldeth
to me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicine, no winter but is remoued by Sommer; for if God doth ſuffer
calamity to befall vs for his glory and our good, he will take it away
againe.<note place="margin">Pſal. 34.19.</note> 
               <hi>For many are the trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles
of the righteous;</hi> but here is the Lords promiſe which is our comfort,
<hi>he will deliuer out of all:</hi> we haue this pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe, which is as the
faithfull witneſſe in heauen for our comfort.</p>
            <p n="7">
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="7"/> 7. Seeing the faithfull onely haue theſe
promiſes; then ought we to labour for a true faith, for this is the
inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment <pb n="14" facs="tcp:17075:10"/>of our redemption, the fruite of the Spirit,
the clo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing of our ſoules, the ioy of the godly, the perfection of the
Church, the euidence by which we hold both our Being,<note place="margin">Mark.
9.24.</note> and well being; <hi>Lord we beleeue, helpe our vnbeleefe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="8">
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="8"/> 8. Laſtly, hath God giuen vs theſe
promiſes? Let vs then learne to giue vnto God that which is Gods, viz.
thankes and praiſe, <hi>For he that offereth me thankes and praiſe,
heho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noureth me,</hi> Pſal. 50.23. Surely (brethren) there is not the leaſt
of his mercies but deſerues a <hi>Quid retribuam.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 116.12. Pſal. 8.4.</note> And <hi>What is man that thou,
art ſo mindfull of him, or the ſonne of man that thou ſor egardeſt him?
&amp;c.</hi> What is to be found in man which might moue the Lord to be ſo
gracious, or to be expected from man which may adde vnto his honour, to whoſe
complete and all-ſufficient fulneſſe, nothing can be added? Surely this
is ſome and all; <hi>Thou ſhalt glorifie me,</hi> Pſal. 50.14. to ſing
and ſay, <hi>Corde, &amp; cordis fide, &amp; fidibus; Glory be to God on
high, on earth peace, goodwill towards men.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Luk.
2.14.</note>Our hearts ſhall be glad when our lips ſpeake his glorie, and
our tongues, ſhall ſing of his righteouſneſſe, while we liue will we
praiſe the Lord, and giue thankes vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to him for a remembrance of his
holineſſe; for to vs hath he giuen theſe promiſes, and therefore
<hi>Regi ſaeculo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum.</hi> 1. Tim. 1. 17. Now, ſaith the Apoſtle; Now is
a time to lift vp your hearts and ſay as he ſaith: <hi>To the King
eternall, immortall, inuiſible, and God onely wiſe, be honour and glory for
euer and euer, Amen.</hi> And of the <hi>ſubiectum</hi> thus far, and now the
<hi>Praedicatum</hi> cometh in place, viz. <hi>theſe pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Promiſes,]</hi>
               <note place="margin">Promiſſiones 1.
Politicae.</note> Promiſes I finde to be generally of two ſorts; politicall
or ciuill, and religious or diuine: vnder the former are ranked all contracts,
compacts, bargaines, and other caſes of commutatiue iuſtice in the
Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth betwixt man and man.<note place="margin">2. Religioſae. Legales.
Euangelicae.</note> Religious promiſes I name ſuch as wherein God doth more
properly challenge a ſhare, as being either the inlargeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts of the bounty
from God to man, or the ingagement of obedience from man <pb n="15" facs="tcp:17075:10"/>to
God: and theſe I find to be double, Legall or Euange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licall,</p>
            <p n="1">1.<note place="margin">Deut. 27.26. Gal. 3.10.</note> Legall,
<hi>ex pacto ſimpliciter; hoc fac &amp; viues,</hi> and againe, <hi>Curſed
is he that continueth not in all things that are written in the Law.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. Euangelicall, <hi>ex pacto ſecundum quid;</hi> being
the free donations of Gods ſoueraigne bounty which worketh all good in all:
<hi>Come vnto me all ye that trauell and are heauie,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Haba. 2.4. Mat. 11.28. Ioh. 3.16. Iſa. 43.25.</note> 
               <hi>&amp;c.
So God loued the world that he, &amp;c. I am he, behold I am he that putteth
away thy vnrighteouſneſſe euen for my names ſake,</hi> Iſa. 43.25.
Theſe are called the promiſes of Gods grace, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe freely giuen, and
ſo performed gratis: the promiſes of the Spirit,<note place="margin">Eph.
1.13. Rom. 10.8.</note> becauſe the Spirit is both the author and ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plier of
them: the words of faith, becauſe they are made with the condition of faith
to apprehend and apply them: they are alſo the promiſes of hope, becauſe
that our har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueſt is in hope onely:<note place="margin">Heb. 6.17.</note>
               <hi>The hope of eternal life which God that cannot lie hath promiſed,
Tit.</hi> 1.2.</p>
            <p>God hath made a couenant with his people, and it is called the
couenant of promiſe, <hi>Eph.</hi> 2.12. the Arke of which teſtimony is the
ſure words of the Goſpell; the keepers and interpreters whereof are his
holy ones, vpon whom he hath put his <hi>Vrim</hi> and <hi>Thummim,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Exod. 28.30.</note> to cauſe Iſrael to heare and know and do
his couenant. The franchiſed li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berties thereof are his promiſes: the
hedges or walles of defence are his iudgements: the feales of aſſurance are
his counſell, his word, his oath, his Sacraments: the earneſt penny is the
ſpirit of ſanctification: the ſtipulators are the Maker and his creature,
God and man; God of his free bounty promiſing all good things for this and a
better life, in Chriſt, for the glory of his goodneſſe; and man
pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſting faith and perfect obedience to his heauenly Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ker. So that
<hi>Subiectum huiusfaederis,</hi> are the ſonnes of God onely, (as I haue
ſhewed before) the ſonnes of promiſe,<note place="margin">Gal.
4.28.</note>Rom. 9.8. ſuch as through faith in a pure conſcience keepe his
commandement alway. This couenant by faith, we ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply <pb n="16" facs="tcp:17075:11"/>it,
we hold it in hope, and ſhew forth the fruites there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of in a godly life and
holy conuerſation. Thus farre we haue walked at large, but now returne I pray
you with me from whence we haue digreſſed, for the bounds of my text do
bound me within the liberties of this holy coue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant; for ſo my text tels vs:
<hi>Has promiſſiones.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Sinne is a bad Miſtreſſe which makes men ſerue long for
little, and in the end paieth with bad wages; <hi>For the wages of ſinne is
death:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rom. 6.23.</note> but our God is liberall as an
Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour, who hath beſtowed a great gift vpon vs in our crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; and that
being loſt, hath giuen vs a greater, and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed greateſt of all. As a
good Phyſitian he healeth vs, and as a good merchant hireth vs, <hi>non vt
duram ſeruiamus ſeruitutem,</hi> but that we ſhould be made coheires with
Chriſt. <hi>Has promiſſiones,</hi> theſe promiſes alſo.</p>
            <p>God hath promiſed ſaluation to his people which haue bene
ſince the world began, from <hi>Adam</hi> to <hi>Abraham,</hi> Gen. 3.15.
from <hi>Abraham</hi> to <hi>Moſes,</hi> Gen. 17.4. from <hi>Moſes</hi> to
Chriſt,<note place="margin">Luk. 18.5. Luk. 20,27. Gal. 4.4.</note> Exod.
14.10. Heb. 9.15. And in the fulneſſe of time God ſent our Sauiour
according to his promiſe, Luk. 1. 54. Act. 3.12. and our Sauiour Chriſt did
mightily ſhew himſelfe to be the Sonne of God, and <hi>the Redeemer of his
people Iſrael,</hi> Luk. 24 19. in who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> all the prophecies, promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes and
figures did meet, as many lines in the center. Theſe promiſes alſo. The
Apoſtle doth alledge onely two texts of theſe promiſes, which are like
the grapes and fruites of Eſchol, which the ſpies brought from the land of
Canaan; (as if he ſhould ſay) By theſe few you may taſte and ſee how
ſweete the Lord is; and if I ſhould labour to go through them all, I
ſuppoſe they are moe in number then the haires of my head, and the plenty
of them would beget want of ſtrength in me to deliuer them. <hi>Moſes</hi>
the man of God doth giue vs to wit,<note place="margin">1. Promiſſio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes
rarae.</note> that theſe promiſes are firſt, <hi>Rarae &amp;
inauditae,</hi> worthy his performance onely, who in all things with his holy
arme doth get himſelfe the victorie.<note place="margin">Pſal.
98.2.</note>Who would haue thought that a wombe of ninety yeares 
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:17075:11"/>barrenneſſe, ſhould be a ioyfull mother of children?
God promiſed it, Gen. 17.17. and he performed it, Gen. 21.6. Who would
imagine that God would bring Iſrael out of Aegypt, thus as it is ſaid, and
after ſo ſtrange a maner, by tentations, by ſignes, and by wonders, by
warre, by a mightie hand, and by a ſtretched out arme, and by great terrors?
according to all that the Lord did for them in Ae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gypt, Deut. 4.34. Who could
haue thought that the Red ſea ſhould be diuided, or Iordan driue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
back?<note place="margin">Exod. 14.21. Ioſh. 10.12. Exod. 16.13. Num.
20.8.</note> or the Moon ſhould ſtay her courſe, and the Sunne forget his
going downe? that Manna ſhould be rained from heauen? that liuing waters
ſhould flow from the flintie rocke? Theſe things God promiſed, Exod.
3.19. and theſe, and greater then theſe the Lord hath done in their due
ſeaſon: for he is the God who made all things of nothing, which quick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth
the dead, and calleth thoſe things which are not, as though they were, Rom.
4.17.</p>
            <p n="2">2.<note place="margin">2. Promiſſio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes certiſſime
Mal. 3.6.</note> Moſt ſure and certaine, as proceeding from the eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitie
and immutabilitie of his will, and verity, with whom is no change, nor ſhadow
of changing. God ſaith concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning him that promiſeth by vow or oath,
<hi>Implebit omne quod promiſit,</hi> Numb. 30.3. <hi>He ſhall not breake
his promiſe; but do according to all that he hath promiſed.</hi> And
ſhall the Lord ſay, and not do it? promiſe, and not performe it? Surely
God ſhall as ſoone not be himſelfe, as his proceedings not be the truth:
he were not omnipotent, but impotent, if it were otherwiſe. Therfore the
Apoſtle doth thus ſtile him, <hi>God that cannot lie, Tit.</hi> 1.2. The
faithfull God, Deut. 7.8. with whom is no change, his promiſes are therefore
<hi>Yea and Amen,</hi> 2. Cor. 1.20. <hi>certiſſimae.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3.<note place="margin">3. Promiſſio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes gratuitae.</note>
               <hi>Gratuitae,</hi> the effects of his mercie and goodneſſe, without any
merite or deſert of ours. Deut. 7.7. <hi>He ſet not his loue vpon you</hi>
(ſaith <hi>Moſes</hi> to <hi>Iſrael</hi>) <hi>nor choſe you becauſe
you were moe in number then other people, for you were the feweſt of all
people: but becauſe the Lord loued you, &amp;c.</hi> And in the riches of his
mercie God choſe this people firſt, and <pb n="18" facs="tcp:17075:12"/>his firſt
promiſe he made to them, Leuit. 26.12. <hi>I will walke with you, I will be
your God, and you ſhall be my people:</hi> yea and enlargeth the ſame,
<hi>Ier.</hi> 31.1. <hi>I will be the God of all the families of Iſrael, and
they ſhal be my people, &amp;c.</hi> When <hi>Adam</hi> ſinned againſt
God, God had compaſſion towards him; yea when he maketh Gods liberalitie
the patrone of his iniquitie, ſaying, <hi>The woman which thou gaueſt me,
&amp;c.</hi> then did he promiſe, <hi>The ſeed of the woman ſhould breake
the Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pents head.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Geneſ. 3.12.</note> Theſe and
the like are <hi>gratuitae promiſſiones,</hi> with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any precedent merit
of man as a motiue to moue him thereunto, the free donations and enlargements
of his goodneſſe and bountie.</p>
            <p n="4">4.<note place="margin">4. Promiſſio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes magnae &amp;
pretioſae.</note> 
               <hi>Magnae &amp; pretioſae:</hi> ſo Saint
<hi>Peter</hi> teacheth vs to eſteem them, 2. <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.3. For theſe,
that our God will be with vs whereſoeuer we go, ruling and aſſiſting vs
in whatſoeuer we do, theſe are <hi>magnae &amp; pretioſae.</hi> Oh how
ſweete are thy promiſes!<note place="margin">Exod. 5.18.</note> Pſal. 119.
He ruleth vs according to his promiſe, not as <hi>Pharaoh</hi> ruled
<hi>Iſrael,</hi> with a rod of iron, toyling them in their taskes of bricke,
allowing no ſtraw; but he commands vs weldoing, and helpes vs to do it; and
when our ſeruice is done of dutie, herein his bountifull dealing paſſeth
our conceiuing, when for a broken ſeruice on earth, he makes a promiſe of
heauen, not as they are now, ſubiect to corruption:<note place="margin">2. Pet.
3.10.</note> 
               <hi>For the heauens ſhall paſſe away with a noiſe, and the
elements ſhall be conſumed with heate;</hi> but as they ſhall be then
refined, moſt glorious and ſtable, for the comfort and crowning of his
Saints; <hi>Magnae &amp; pretioſae.</hi> So that as a Father ſaith, The
children of God hauing taſted hereof in the life to come, do mourne and
grieue in the heauens, that their repentance was no ſooner, their
thank<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſſe no more, and their obedience no greater to glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rifie God on
earth: ſo that as it is ſaid of the glorious Church, <hi>Quàm
mirabilia de te narrantur, ô Ciuitas Dei:</hi> Oh how great and
wonderfull things are ſpoken of thee, O thou Citie of God! ſuch are his
promiſes according to the excellencie of his wiſedome and power, <hi>Magnae
&amp; pretioſae.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="19" facs="tcp:17075:12"/>
            <p>And in the fift place, that we may inherite the promiſes,<note place="margin">5. Promiſſio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes futurae.</note>I muſt informe you, that
they are <hi>futurae,</hi> viz. of things to come, the promiſes of hope.
<hi>Our life</hi> (ſaith <hi>Paul</hi>) <hi>is hid with Chriſt:</hi> and
<hi>it appeares not what we ſhall be.</hi> Peraduen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, ſome will ſay,
better to haue ſomething certaine. But to them I ſay, our hope is not a
dead but a liuely hope:<note place="margin">1. Pet. 1.3. 2. Pet 3.8.</note> not
depending vpon man, whoſe breath is in his noſtrils, but vpon our God, with
whom one day is as a thouſand yeares, and a thouſand yeares as one day. The
Apoſtle ſaith, <hi>God is faithfull:</hi> and, We know whom we haue
beleeued. If our life therefore be a warfare, our hope is an helmet. Eph. 6. if
a ſea-faring, hope is our anchor, to ſtay our ſhips in dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger,<note place="margin">Act. 27.33.</note>till the day appeare, Act. 28. And in a word, in
all things this is our ſtay, God is faithfull; he hath promiſed, and will
performe it, but all in his due time; his (I ſay) and not ours,<note place="margin">Pſal. 40.1.</note> that we ſhould keepe our ſoules ſtill
waiting on the Lord; therefore they are <hi>futurae.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="6">6.<note place="margin">6. Promiſſio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes
auguſtiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſimae.</note> To compriſe many in one, and not to totall all
in iuſt account: in briefe, the promiſes of God are generall, par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular,
reall, perſonall, conditionall, free, temporall, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternall, who can go
through them all? The Apoſtle ſaith, that the Angels looke with amazement
at the myſterie of our redemption, to behold the infinite oddes betwixt Gods
greatneſſe and our vileneſſe: ſo to let paſſe the great and
precious promiſes of his word and Spirit, the care and miniſtery of his
Angels and creatures; and to conſider that our very corrections ſhall do vs
good, Pſal. 94.12. that he will turne our beds in our ſickneſſe,
Pſal. 41. take care of the haires of our heads, Matth. 10.<note place="margin">Matth. 10.30.</note> it will driue vs to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtoniſhment to
conſider; for there is no end of his good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe. The heathen Captaine
which had care to waſh his ſouldiers wounds, they could not ſufficiently
honour him with praiſes: ſurely if the God of glorie and Captaine of his
Church, ſhould do ſuch and ſo great things for vs, let vs ſay with
Saint <hi>Paul,</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>:<note place="margin">Rom.
11.33.</note>
               <hi>O the deepneſſe of the riches both of the wiſedome and
loue of <pb n="20" facs="tcp:17075:13"/>God, and his wayes that are paſt finding
out!</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thus farre we haue dealt in theſe promiſes at rouers (as I may
ſay) and now to bring them home to our hearts, which are the true marke.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe. </seg>1</label> Are theſe promiſes <hi>rarae
&amp; inauditae?</hi> Let vs hence learne to ioy in the ſame; <hi>Oh how
ſweete are thy words vnto my throate, yea ſweeter then honey vnto my
mouth!</hi> Pſal. 119.103. And againe, <hi>Thy teſtimonies haue I claimed
as mine heritage for euer, for they are the very ioy of my heart,</hi> Pſal.
119.111. Thus <hi>Sara</hi> reioyced, and called others to reioyce with her,
Gen. 21.6. <hi>God hath cauſed me to reioyce, all that heare will reioyce
with me.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Luk. 1.46.</note> 
               <hi>My ſoule doth magnifie
the Lord, and my ſpirit reioyceth in God my Sauiour:</hi> this is the ſong
of that bleſſed euer Virgin mother, who reioyced in theſe
pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> Secondly, are they <hi>certiſſimae?</hi>
Then let vs beleeue and truſt in them, by the example of our father
<hi>Abraham,</hi> who beleeued aboue hope. So though they are aboue, beſide,
contrary to reaſon, yet knowing that God is pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erfull and able, faithfull,
and ſo ready to make his promiſe good, let vs be ſtrengthened in faith,
and giue glorie to God, Rom. 4.17. Yea and in the ſecond place, truſt and
relie on his promiſed mercies: for hereby we haue acceſſe to challenge
God both for ſafetie and ſaluation. Thus <hi>Moſes</hi> is bold to charge
God with his promiſe, on the behalfe of Iſrael, Exod. 32.13. <hi>Remember
Abraham, Iſaac and Iacob, to whom thou ſwareſt, &amp;c.</hi> and it
followeth, ver 14. <hi>Then the Lord changed his mind from the euill,
&amp;c.</hi> An in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance of like nature we haue in Deut. 9.27.
<hi>Dauid</hi> had the like refuge in extremitie, <hi>Lord, where are thy
former mercies which thou ſwareſt to Dauid in thy truth?</hi> Pſal.
89.49. Calling to minde therefore the certaintie of theſe promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, let vs
by the example of <hi>Iacob</hi> commit our ſelues to Gods tuition and
defence, Gen. 32.9. for they are <hi>cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſſimae.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> 3. Are they <hi>Gratuitae,</hi> the free
donations of his good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe <pb n="21" facs="tcp:17075:13"/>&amp; mercy? Then where are
the blind merits of Monks and Friars, and the workes of ſupererogation of
inſolent Ieſuites? their pretended merits either of condignitie or
congruity, are altogether repugnant to the freedome of theſe promiſes: a
debt of deſert as hire to a labourer, or of duty as of thankfulneſſe to a
benefactour, farre be it that we ſhould claime any ſuch due from God to vs;
for to vs belongeth ſhame and confuſion,<note place="margin">Gen.
32.10.</note> being leſſe then the leaſt of Gods mercies: It is his great
mercie that we are not conſumed, and therefore in all theſe
promiſes,<note place="margin">Pſal. 115.1.</note> 
               <hi>Not vnto vs Lord, not
vnto vs, but vnto thy name giue the glorie.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4">
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> 4. Are they <hi>magnae &amp;
pretioſae?</hi> Hence then let vs learne to be thankfull. When one told
<hi>Dauid Sauls</hi> intendment to make him his ſonne in law, he anſwered,
<hi>For what? See<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth it a ſmall thing vnto you to be ſonne in law to a
King?</hi>
               <note place="margin">Sam. 18.18.</note> 
               <hi>what am I? or what is my
life, or the familie of my father in Iſrael, that I ſhould be ſonne in
law to a King?</hi> His caſe fits with ours, but in ſome reſpects it doth
not; for what compariſon be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt <hi>Dauid</hi> and vs, or analogy twixt God
and <hi>Saul? Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uid</hi> had deſerued well of his countrey; and againe,
though he were ſonne in law, yet ſhould not be heire to the Crowne: but for
our ſelues, I ſay not, what am I? but what are we, or our fathers houſe?
was not our father an A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morite, and our mother an Hittite, drowned in
ſuperſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, ſold vnto ſinne, and full of ignorance? I ſay of the
beſt, which can beſt expreſſe his mind and meaning, that he cannot
expreſſe his owne vnworthineſſe. And betwixt God and <hi>Saul,</hi>
what ſhould I ſay? who is the <hi>Saul</hi> of <hi>Sauls,</hi> in whoſe
reſpect all the Princes of the earth are but waſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pots, vnto whom the
Angels are miniſters, accounting it their greateſt honour to do him
ſeruice, yea and the hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uens and the earth do bow downe vnto him:&amp; yet
vs <hi>tan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tillos &amp; tales,</hi> ſo weake, and ſo vnworthy, hath he
crow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned with his honours, to make vs ſonnes and daughters to himſelfe, to
reigne and rule for euer in his glory. Praiſe ye the Lord therefore all ye
his Saints, for it becometh the <pb n="22" facs="tcp:17075:14"/>Saints right well to be
thankfull.</p>
            <p n="5">
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="5"/> 5. Are they <hi>Futurae,</hi> of good
things to come? Then it behoueth vs, <hi>expectare impletionem,</hi> to waite
on his mercies vntill he heare vs, helpe vs, heale vs, and crowne vs:
<hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tientia vobis opus eſt,</hi> Heb. 10.36. <hi>Ye haue need of patience,
that when you haue done the will of God you might inherite the promiſe:</hi>
therefore muſt we become followers of them which through faith and
patience,<note place="margin">Heb. 12.1.</note> obtained the promiſes.</p>
            <p n="6">
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="6"/> 6. And laſtly, are they ſo generall,
ſpeciall, ſuch as hath bene ſaid, <hi>tam auguſtiſſimae,</hi> ſo
glorious, and in extent ſo large and liberall? Let vs then make the ſame
vſe of them which the Apoſtle here maketh in this place; viz. Let vs obey
them, <hi>Let vs cleanſe our ſelues from all filthineſſe of the fleſh
and ſpirit.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Where in the tranſition of the point from the Antece<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent,
<hi>(Seeing we haue theſe promiſes)</hi> to the Conſequent: <hi>let vs
cleanſe our ſelues, &amp;c.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Doct.</note>
obſerue,</p>
            <p>The promiſes of God in Chriſt are the ground of obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience:
the Apoſtle therefore to this purpoſe maketh the ſame connexion, Tit.
2.11. <hi>The grace of God which bringeth ſaluation to all men hath appeared,
and teacheth vs to deny vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>godlineſſe and worldly luſts, and that we
ſhould liue godlily and righteouſly and ſoberly in this preſent
world:</hi> the grace of God teacheth vs not to do vngodlines but to deny it,
to cleanſe our ſelues from all the outrages and vngodlineſſe of the
hand and tong, yea and all ſinfull luſts of the heart: &amp; that we
ſhould liue towards God <hi>piè,</hi> towards others
<hi>iuſtè,</hi> and to our ſelues <hi>ſobriè.</hi> The
grace of God teacheth vs to do eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſo as I haue ſaid. The promiſes of
God are the ground of obedience, <hi>I beſeech you by the mercies of
God,</hi> ſaith Saint <hi>Paul,</hi> Rom. 12.1. <hi>that you giue vp your
bodies and ſoules a li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing ſacrifice vnto God. &amp;c.</hi> Where he makes
Gods mercies the onely motiue to obedience; for howſoeuer ſome do his will
of compulſion, becauſe they dare do no other, yet, <hi>plures colligit
amor;</hi> and good men loue God for him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, euen of zeale to his glory.
The Lord hath two ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary <pb n="23" facs="tcp:17075:14"/>Heralds of obedience, viz. his
promiſes, and his threats: <hi>Aut ſequeris aut traheris,</hi> either his
mercies to al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lure vs, or his iudgements to terrifie vs; and therefore we ſay
on behalfe of his mercies, that the liberty of a Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian doth
neceſſarily imply (not laſineſſe) but holineſſe: and when we
ſay that the promiſes of God are <hi>gratuitae,</hi> our meaning is <hi>ex
parte antecedente non conſequente;</hi> free on Gods part to vs, for no
inducement in vs to moue him to compaſſion; but not ſo on our part
towards him, for they are done vpon condition of our obedience. It is in his
promiſes as in his threatnings, they all runne (not ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolutely but) with a
prouiſo, expreſſed or at leaſt wiſe vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood. <hi>Si niſi non
eſſet, perfectum quidlibet eſſet,</hi> Were it not for conditions and
exceptions, our end was preſent deſtruction, <hi>Except you repent you
ſhall all periſh:</hi> but the <hi>Niſi</hi> comes in like a Repriueall
betwixt the ſentence and the execution day: and as it is in the caſe of
threatning, ſo likewiſe of promiſe; for there is a twofold
<hi>niſi,</hi> of repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, and of obedience, ſo that except we performe
the conditions, we haue no part nor claime in the promiſes. The charge of
<hi>Ioſua</hi> makes it plaine, <hi>Ioſua</hi> 23. as that chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter doth
dilate at large; neither need I ſtand to cleare this point, that all the
promiſes run with the condition of ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſſe, for all the Sermons of the
Prophets and Apoſtles, giue witneſſe to this purpoſe: <hi>And this is
the will of God, euen your ſanctification: God hath purchaſed you to be a
people,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Tit. 2.14.</note> 
               <hi>holy and peculiar to
himſelfe, that you ſhould be zealous of good workes:</hi> &amp; therefore
Gods loue and our obedience, which God hath ioyned together, let no man put
aſunder.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe. </seg>1</label> Are the promiſes of God the
ground of obedience?Then our doctrine is not a doctrine of liberty, neither is
the calling of a Chriſtian a calling of eaſe; for we preach not mercies, or
promiſes, that men ſhould liue as they liſt. Should a malefactor contemne
his Prince becauſe he is mercifull, or a ſonne diſobey his father for his
loue and affection? This I ſay, that precedent promiſes can purchaſe 
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:17075:15"/>no licenſe for ſubſequent ſinnes. It is not our
hope, but the profeſſion of our hope that ſhall ſaue vs. Saint
<hi>Paule</hi> therefore ſaith, 1. Cor. 5.7. <hi>Purge out the old leauen,
that you may be a new lumpe, for Chriſt our paſſeouer is ſacrificed for
vs.</hi> Becauſe he was crucified for vs, let vs not crucifie him againe, but
rather becauſe he was ſacrificed for vs, let vs ſacrifice our ſelues
for him, in obedience and ſanctity. For Gods mercie and our obedience muſt
be ioyned together, and they that turne away obedience and faith from their
hearts, turne away Chriſts merits and mercies from their ſoules; and they
that will not weepe ouer him whom their ſinnes haue wounded, he ſhall neuer
bleede ouer them that their ſinnes my be pardoned: and therefore,</p>
            <p n="2">2. See the calumniation of our quarrelling aduerſaries,
the aduerſaries of the grace of God, the Church of Rome, which charge vs with
that we neuer taught, God he knowes our innocency, viz. that we teach promiſe
with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out obedience, faith without workes; and therefore that we are
ſolifidians, and teach a doctrine of licenciouſneſſe to all impietie.
But to theſe I ſay, that we haue not ſo taught,<note place="margin">Eph.4.20.</note> neither haue we ſo learned Chriſt; for we
teach, faith without workes to be a dead faith, and the promiſes of God
without our obedience ſhall do vs no good; for howſoeuer they are
ſufficient in themſelues, yet are they not effectuall in vs. But to bring
home their ſinne to their owne doores, to pay them with their owne coine, or
ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to ſtrike the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> with the rod which they haue prepared: may I not
ſay, and experience beare me witneſſe, that I ſpeake the truth in
Chriſt and lie not? Is not their do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine a doctrine of liberty,<note place="margin">1 Tim.4.1.</note> or rather of diuels? which make merchandiſe of
ſinne, as of fleſh in the ſhambles, <hi>making ſhipwrack of faith and a
good conſcience;</hi> and hauing clad them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues with the figge leaues of
a blind diſpenſation from a Popiſh broker, they bluſh not at moſt
direfull proiects, but walke ſecure in the machinations and executions of all
villany. What ſhall I name that which is not to be na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med <pb n="25" facs="tcp:17075:15"/>amongſt Chriſtians, the tolleration of ſtewes, and the like
(which yet is not paralelled among the nations?) A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>las, <hi>paruaqueror,</hi>
theſe be but trifles.<note place="margin">Seneca.</note> 
               <hi>Audent aliquid
breui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus gyaris &amp; carcere dignum:</hi> To kill a King, or poiſon a
Prince, to blow vp a Senate, to defie God, deface reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, plot treaſons,
ſpoile a nation; theſe and the like are patronized among thoſe Satanicall
ſpirits, and the actors canonized for worthies, and their acts for workes of
ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pererogation. I might inſtance in their intended deſolati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons in the
dayes of our famous <hi>Deborah,</hi> the memoriall of whoſe name ſhall be
bleſſed for euer: and their helliſh treaſons now in the dayes of our
happie <hi>Ioſhua</hi> (whoſe yeares the Lord make as many ages, and fill
all his dayes with peace) a Monarch for his power, and a man after Gods owne
heart, ſo famous for his learning, ſo learned in religion, and religious in
profeſſion, innocent from wrong, peaceable in his wayes, and mercifull to
all, if not too mercifull to them; and yet did not theſe infernall
ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits, Antichriſtian pioners and Romiſh Mold warpes, ſeeke to
extinguiſh this glorious light, and the life of the whole land, <hi>vno
tactu, vno ictu, vno nictu,</hi> with one blow, ſulphuri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous blaſt, in the
twinkling of an eye, to haue diſmembred and cruſhed together the
gouernment, counſell, wiſedom, learning, iuſtice and religion of God in
the whole land? <hi>Oh inauditum nefas, oh nefandum ſcelus! Oh vnſpeakable
vil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lanie,</hi> eſpecially to be countenanced or canonized but in the Rolles
of hel, or by a Pope a diuel incarnate: and doth not the Pope giue libertie and
diſpenſations for the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitting of the ſame? is not this a doctrine of
libertie, which doth giue libertie to make themſelues (as it were) drunke
with the bloud of ſo many worthies? I dare be bold to ſay, that all the
Maſſes, Dirges, Trentals, ſmoakie fumes and polluted lip-ſeruice, and
(as the Apoſtle ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth) <hi>beggerly rudiments,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gal.4.9.</note> or (if you will) coſening ſhifts of all the
idolatrous Ieſuites, Monkes and Friers, and adde to them all the Engliſh
calues, begotten by the buls of <pb n="26" facs="tcp:17075:16"/>Rome, cannot waſh this
one bloudie ſinne from the Popes bloud-guiltie ſoule.</p>
            <p n="3">
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> 3. What ſhall I ſay of the world, who
from the promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes of God take libertie to ſinne? For God and the world are
contrary: and it is to be obſerued, that Gods Saints out of his promiſes
deduce arguments of obedience, which worldly libertines do not. <hi>I wil dwell
among you: I will walke with you: I will be your God: I will be your Father,
&amp;c.</hi> theſe are Gods promiſes, and the Apoſtle reades them in
feare and feeling, <hi>Seeing we haue theſe promiſes, let vs cleanſe our
ſelues;</hi> but the world reades them in licentiouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, Seeing we haue
theſe promiſes, let vs defile our ſelues.<note place="margin">Pſal.130.4.</note> 
               <hi>There is mercie with God, therefore
ſhall he be feared,</hi> ſaith <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uid;</hi> therefore we need not feare
him, ſaith the world. <hi>The time of our abiding here is ſhort, therefore
let vs vſe the world as though we vſed it not,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1.
Cor. 7.29.</note> ſaith the Apoſtle; but let vs vſe it while we haue
it,<note place="margin">1. Cor. 15.32.</note> 
               <hi>Let vs eate and drinke, for to
morrow we ſhall die,</hi> ſaith the libertine. Theſe things being thus, I
do the leſſe wonder to reade what is written: <hi>Know ye not, my
bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren, that the wiſedome of the world is fooliſhneſſe?</hi> and,
<hi>the loue of the world is enmitie with God,</hi> Iam. 4. By which
oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition you may perceiue that there are two ſorts of men here aimed at;
the former, ſuch as are not named, nor wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy the naming, which promiſe
themſelues libertie, and yet are themſelues the ſeruants of corruption,
2. Pet. 2.19. <hi>Who turne the grace of God into wantonneſſe,</hi>
beaſts without reaſon, men without humanitie, as bad as the horſe and
mule which haue no vnderſtanding, their conſciences are feared with an hote
iron, and are ſetled on the lees of their iniquities, which make a mocke of
Gods promiſes, and ſay <hi>Where is the promiſe of his coming?</hi> 2.
Pet. 3.3. beaſts led in ſenſualitie, <hi>which haue giuen themſelues to
worke vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleanneſſe, euen with greedineſſe,</hi> Epheſ 4. a
generation of vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers, and vicious brood,<note place="margin">Math. 23.33.</note>
more degenerate then <hi>Nebuchad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nezzar</hi> from a King to a beaſt, for
whom is reſerued the damnation of hell; <hi>Be not therefore companions with
them, <pb n="27" facs="tcp:17075:16"/>for you were once darkneſſe, but now are you
light in the Lord,</hi> Eph. 5.7. and therefore labour to be of them which are
the children of light, the ſonnes of God, and heires with Chriſt according
to theſe promiſes, in whom reſteth the ſpirit of feare and
feeling.<note place="margin">Prou. 28.14.</note>
            </p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> Laſtly, that we may ſo do as the promiſes
moue and teach vs, viz. forſake ſinne, and embrace holineſſe; let vs
euermore conſider the ſufferings of Chriſt for ſinne, and his
promiſes mouing him thereunto. Can the adulterer take delight in the ſinne
of the fleſh, conſidering his fleſh that was wounded for his ſinnes?
Could the voluptuous and feathered gallants take ſuch ſurfets of
pleaſure, ſeeing Chriſt ſweating and ſhedding ſtreames of water
&amp; bloud? Could the horſeleach the vnſatiable ſeruant of Mammon ſay
as the Poet ſaith, <hi>Populus me ſibilat, mihi plaudo ipſe do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mi,</hi>
ſo bleſſe himſelfe in his wretched gettings, and know Chriſt pierced
to the heart for getting of them? Or can we heare of his bleeding and
ſuffering, and yet continue in ſinning? Can we loue that, which God at all
times and in all places hath ſo proteſted that he hates? He could not
en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dure it in heauen; <hi>Angeli detruduntur,</hi> the Angels were throwne
downe headlong for it; he could not endure it on earth, <hi>Chriſtus
crucifigitur,</hi> his owne Sonne died for it: nor yet in hell, <hi>Inferni
cruciantur,</hi> whole legions are tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mented for it. Let vs therfore deale
with ſinne for his ſake, as he was dealt withall for ours. The Iewes
purſued him in his life, crucified him in his death,<note place="margin">Math.
27.60. Auguſtine.</note> and when he was dead, rolled a ſtone vpon him:
ſo let vs (as <hi>Auguſtine</hi> coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelleth) vpon the croſſe of
repentance betweene theſe two grand theeues, the world and the fleſh,
crucifie ſinne, pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſue it in the riſing, reſiſt it in the growing,
reſt not vntill we haue killed it, and then (as neuer ſafe enough) let vs
rolle a ſtone vpon it, neuer to reuiue the ſame or the like againe. And in
concluſion, <hi>Seeing we haue theſe promiſes,</hi> merits and mercies
for the remiſſion of ſinnes, <hi>let vs cleanſe our ſelues from all
filthineſſe of the fleſh and ſpirit, an grow vp <pb n="28" facs="tcp:17075:17"/>to
full holineſſe in the feare of God.</hi> My text, you ſee, hath brought
vs now from the antecedent promiſes to the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequent inferred, <hi>Let vs
cleanſe, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Which concluſion is a ſure perſwaſion to a regenerate
life; wherein is contained the two parts of ſanctification:</p>
            <list>
               <item>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> 1. <hi>Remotio mali, Let vs cleanſe our
ſelues from, &amp;c.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> 2. <hi>Subſtitutio boni, And grow vp to
full holineſſe, &amp;c.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <p>Furthermore, in the concluſion obſerue the two gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall parts
of a propoſition.</p>
            <list>
               <item>
                  <list>
                     <item>
                        <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> 1. <hi>Subiectum, Vs: Let vs cleanſe,
&amp;c.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> 2. <hi>Praedicatum,</hi> in the two
parts forenamed,</item>
                  </list> 
                  <list>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Remotione mali, Let vs cleanſe, &amp;c.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Subſtitutione boni, And grow vp to,
&amp;c.</hi>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </item>
            </list>
            <p>To take them then in order as they are propounded. And firſt of
the <hi>Subiectum, Vs.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Subiectum.</note>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Vs]</hi> If we enquire who are here meant, we ſhall finde
them the ſame with the former <hi>(We)</hi> viz. <hi>Paul</hi> and the
Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rinthians beleeuers; theſe are they that muſt cleanſe them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues.
From whence obſerue,</p>
            <p>There is droſſe in the beſt,<note place="margin">Doctr.</note>
euen the moſt regenerate, and that in all the parts and powers of the fleſh
and ſpirit. <hi>All fleſh is as graſſe,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iam.
1.10.</note> and full of frailties; there is no come but may be blaſted, and
no ſoule but may be corrupted. In the faireſt roſe, a man may find a
canker; euen ſo the holieſt man hath his gifts, with ſundry
imperfections. The ſtouteſt man may haue a fall; and the iuſt man falls
ſeuen times a day. Whoſoeuer then is without ſinne, let him caſt the
firſt ſtone at his fellow. <hi>in many things</hi> (ſaith the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle)
<hi>we ſinne all.</hi> And therefore ſaith <hi>Iob,</hi> though a iuſt
man, <hi>If I ſhall iuſtifie my ſelfe, my owne mouth ſhall condemne me:
if I will put forth my ſelfe for a perfect man, he will proue me a wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked
doer,</hi> Iob 9.20. And <hi>Dauid</hi> to like purpoſe (though a man after
Gods owne heart) cries out, <hi>Heale my ſoule, O Lord, for I haue ſinned
againſt thee.</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. Ioh. 1.10.</note> And <hi>who ſo
faith that he is without ſinne, is a lier, and the truth is not in him,</hi>
1. Ioh. 1.10. <pb n="29" facs="tcp:17075:17"/>There is ſinne therefore in the godly
aſwell as the vngod<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, but with difference; the one ſinnes of infirmity,
the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with conſent and approbation: in the one ſin dwels, <hi>peccatum
inhabitans,</hi> in the other it reignes,<note place="margin">Peccatum
in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>habitans &amp; regnans.</note> 
               <hi>peccatum reg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nans.</hi> It is in the
godly as a fire which he laboureth to quench: but in the wicked a conſuming
fire, which he takes pleaſure to kindle. Of the godly Saint <hi>Iohn</hi>
ſaith, they commit not ſinne, 1. Ioh. 3. 9. Howſoeuer they of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend, yet
it is with reluctation of ſpirit, they are preuen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted and ouertaken vnawares,
Gal. 6.1. But the wicked commit ſinne, and continue therein; but their
<hi>commtiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus</hi> will ſeale them a <hi>mittimus,</hi> and ſend them to
hell bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy and ſoule. This then is the difference: The godly ſay with
<hi>Dauid, Waſh me throughly from mine iniquitie &amp; cleanſe me from my
ſinne, for I acknowledge my tranſgreſſions and my ſinne is before me;
againſt thee, thee onely haue I ſinned and done euill in thy ſight,
&amp;c.</hi> Pſal. 51.2.3. He humbles himſelfe with the prodigo,<note place="margin">Luk.
15.</note> 
               <hi>I haue ſinned againſt heauen and againſt thee</hi> ô
Father of my fleſh and ſpirit. Knockes his breaſt as the arke of all
iniquity, and ſighing ſaies:<note place="margin">Luk. 18.13.</note> 
               <hi>God
be merci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full to me a ſinner.</hi> But the wicked <hi>Ieremy</hi> deſcribes
them thus, <hi>They bluſh at nothing, they haue an harlots
forehead;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ier.</note> it is meate and drinke to them to
commit wickedneſſe: and <hi>Peter</hi> ſaith: <hi>They wonder</hi> at the
children of God,<note place="margin">Pet.</note> 
               <hi>becauſe they runne not
riot as they do:</hi> and in one word, in the one ſinne reignes, but in the
other ſinne onely remaines.</p>
            <p n="1">
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſon. </seg>1</label> 1. Becauſe we haue
ſucked corruption from the breaſts of our mothers, yea not onely borne, but
conceiued in ſinne, Pſal. 51.5. <hi>Nemo naeſcitur ſanctus;</hi> and
therefore in that we are heires in hope, <hi>Non tam generatio quàm
regene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ratio spectanda eſt;</hi> euery <hi>Natus</hi> muſt be
<hi>renatus:</hi> for it is written, <hi>Except you be borne againe,
&amp;c.</hi> Ioh. 3.5. Yea and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>generation is not preſently perfected but
by degrees: as a wilde oliue tree growing out of a ſtone-wall, the boughes
and branches thereof may be cut and corrected, but the roote remaining, by the
ſent of water will be rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy <pb n="30" facs="tcp:17075:18"/>to ſproute anew, till the
wall be broken and the roote pulled vp; ſo old <hi>Adam</hi> who remaining in
the wals of this earthly tabernacle, may be curbed and ſuppreſſed that
ſinne reigne not in our mortall bodies, yet will he be prompt and readie to
bring forth fruites of vnrighteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, vpon occaſion, till the
walles of this earthly houſe be deſtroied by death, to be raiſed againe
more gloriouſly.</p>
            <p n="2">
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> 2. Becauſe our ſanctification is but
in part, as Saint <hi>Paule</hi> doth diſpute the point, Rom. 7.22. <hi>For I
delight in the law of God after the inward man, but I ſee another law in my
members rebelling againſt the law of my minde.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> 3. Becauſe by this we might be humbled
with our wants, and keepe our ſoules waiting on Gods mercy, and more
earneſtly endeauour to be in Chriſt. <hi>Paule</hi> for our example was
filled with the Spirit, and had abundance of reuelations, taken vp into the
third heauen, and heard ſuch myſteries, as is not poſſible for the
tongue of man to vtter: but leſt he ſhould be exalted out of meaſure,
there is giuen him, <hi>ſtimulus concupiſcentiae,</hi> and the
meſſenger of Satan was ſent to buffet him, 2. Cor. 12.7. For as the
diuell brings euill out of good, ſo God brings good out of euill, cauſing
the wants of his Saints and their infirmities, yea their ſinnes which the
diuell worketh as poyſon to kill them, to be for their welfare in his
prouidence, and po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions to cure them; for by theſe he humbleth them; ſo
that all things worke for their good.</p>
            <p n="1">
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe. </seg>1</label> 1.<note place="margin">Rom.
8.28.</note> Is there droſſe in the beſt? Then can we expect no
iuſtification by our workes, for ſinne cannot iuſtifie ſinne, and in
our beſt actions are manifold imperfections, Gal. 2.16. <hi>Know that a man
is not iuſtified by the deedes of the law, but by the faith of Ieſus
Chriſt, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> 2. See here the Errour of the
Cathariſts, which hold that after regeneration none can ſinne; for ſay
they, As of a wilde tree the old top being cut off, and new impes in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>graſted,
it bringeth fruite no more wilde, but good fruite; ſo we being ingrafted into
Chriſt ſinne not: grounding on <pb n="31" facs="tcp:17075:18"/>that text,
<hi>Whoſoeuer is borne of God ſinneth not.</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Ioh.
3.9.</note> But I anſwer, that their <hi>Simile</hi> holds not: and I put
this queſtion whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther they make Chriſt or the man to be the ſtocke ſo
graf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted; for we know that the fruite is good by vertue of the impe and not of
the ſtocke: if then we are the impes in Chriſt, by their reaſon he
ſhould be made fruitfull and good by vs: but if they make man the ſtocke,
and Chriſt the impe or grafts, I ſay the new man Chriſt ſinnes not;
&amp; ſo ſaith Saint Ioh. 3.9. But yet they muſt remember the old
ſtock, &amp; to looke to the roote which will not be pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently changed,
but will yeeld ſtill wilde branches bearing fruites of
vnrighteouſneſſe.</p>
            <p n="3">
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> 3. This teacheth vs, by their droſſe
to purge our ſelues, and not to take liberty to ſinne becauſe they haue
ſinned. Becauſe one man hath fallen into the ſea and ſcaped drow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning,
ſhall a man leape into the ſea? this were high preſu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>p<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. Build not
therefore vpon their ruines, for their infir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mities are written for our
inſtruction, to ſhew that God will not ſpare ſinne whereſoeuer he
findes it, no not in his Saints, but doth regiſter and chronicle their
reproches to all poſterities, like <hi>Lots</hi> wife which was turned into a
pil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar of ſalt, and ſet vp as examples to ſeaſon others;<note place="margin">Gen. 19.26.</note> and to giue vs warning, vpon whom the ends of
the world are come, that whereas for them there was a cure behind, the
ſacrifice of the Lambe, which was not yet ſlaine, but for ſuch as ſhall
now ſinne Chriſt dieth no more,<note place="margin">Reu. 22.7.</note> for his
next coming ſhall be in iudgemen.</p>
            <p n="4">
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> 4. 
<note place="margin">Mat. 7.1.</note> We are taught to beware of
raſh iudgement to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demne a man for ſome few infirmities, as becauſe
one pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſor is diſcouered for an hypocrite, therefore to cenſure
all, as if all the Apoſtles were to be condemned for <hi>Iudas.</hi> Should a
ſonne deſpiſe his father becauſe he is poore? or the blind diſdaine
to be directed by the lame, becauſe he cannot walke with him? Surely we are
not to contemne the meaneſt gifts; for in the building of the Temple all haue
not the chiefeſt place, but ſome ſquare the ſtones, <pb n="32" facs="tcp:17075:19"/>ſome fit the mortar, ſome carry, and ſome place the worke.
<hi>Ex quouis ligno non ſit Mercurius:</hi> ſo to the building of the
Temple of Chriſt,<note place="margin">1 Cor. 3.13. 1 Cor. 12.</note> ſome
bring ſtubble, ſome ſtraw, ſome mortar, euery man according to the
meaſure of faith which he hath receiued, and in the end euery mans worke
ſhall be tried by the fire; and till the end let all this be vſed to
edification. If none ſhould ſtudy phyſick but thoſe that could cure all
diſeaſes, we ſhould haue no Phyſicians; and if none ſhould ſerue
God but thoſe that could ſerue God perfectly, we ſhould haue none to
ſerue God. Which of you caſteth away a crackt peece of gold, or a broken
ſiluer cup? No more are we to deſpiſe the graces of God in a meane
perſon though imperfect; for he which hath recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued moſt hath many wants,
and a wiſe mans iudgement begins at his owne houſe.</p>
            <p n="5">
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="5"/> 5. And laſtly, we learne not to brag and
boaſt of our broken ſeruice, but to be humbled with our manifold wants and
infirmities. When we haue preached all our liues, and praied with neuer ſo
entire affection, and labou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red our callings with neuer ſo great diligence,
we are al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>together vnprofitable, hauing left more vndone then thoſe we haue
performed: yea and whatſoeuer we haue done is in ſuch great
weakneſſe,<note place="margin">Pſal. 143. 2.</note> that <hi>Lord, if
thouſhouldeſt marke what is done amiſſe, who ſhall be able to abide
it.</hi> In con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluſion therefore let him haue the glory in all things, who
giueth ſeede vnto the ſower and bread to him that nee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth,<note place="margin">1. Cor. 9.10.</note>who worketh in vs both to will and to do: and
we let vs cleanſe our ſelues; for when we haue done all, we are ſtill
vnprofitable ſeruants.<note place="margin">Luk. 17.10.</note> And of the
<hi>(Subiectum)</hi> thus farre; now to the <hi>praedicate,</hi> wherein is
ſet downe <hi>Remotio mali,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Remotio ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>li in 5.</note>
viz. <hi>Let vs cleanſe our ſelues from all filthineſſe of the fleſh
and ſpirit.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Wherin obſerue the fiue forenamed paſſages.</p>
            <list>
               <item>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> 1. The property of the worke,
<hi>Cleanſe.]</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> 2. The propriety of the perſons <hi>[our
ſelues]</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> 3. The matter to be wrought on
<hi>[filthineſſe]</hi>
               </item>
               <pb n="33" facs="tcp:17075:19"/>
               <item>4. The generality of the taske <hi>[all
filthineſſe]</hi>
               </item>
               <item>5. The ſpeciality of the parts and powers infected
<hi>[fleſh and ſpirit.]</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <p>For the firſt, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Cleanſe]</hi> which is a metaphoricall ſpeech taken from
outward waſhing: for as filth is done away by water, ſo by the helpe of
Gods Spirit, muſt we cleanſe our ſelues from ſinne.</p>
            <p>You ſhall reade to this purpoſe, diuers lawes and ſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tutes
in Iſrael: of cleanſing the Altar, Exod, 29. of clean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing the Leaper,
Leuit. 13. of cleanſing the houſe of the Lord, 2. Chron. 29. of cleanſing
Iudah and Ieruſalem, 2. Chron. 34. of cleanſing the people, with the gates
and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trances of their cities and houſes, Nehem. 11. And theſe lawes, we
know, were typicall, hauing reſemblance of things to come: and the ſame God
being our God, requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth the ſame of vs in ſubſtance, which was
prefigured in theſe ceremonies and ſhadowes. For the Altar is our heart,
<hi>Cor mundum,</hi> Pſal. 51. <hi>a cleane heart:</hi> the leproſie is our
ſinne, which ſtings like a ſcorpion, and infects like a leproſie: the
houſe of the Lord, are our bodies and ſoules, which are the temples of the
holy Ghoſt: Iudah and Ieru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalem, are the Iſrael of God, which muſt be
holy euen as he is holy: and the people and their gates, are we here
aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſembled, whom of no people, he hath made a people, that we ſhould
ſanctifie our gates, viz. our affections and acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, through which the
Spirit of grace ſhall go in and out. <hi>Lift vp your heads, O ye gates, and
be ye lift vp ye euer laſting doores:</hi> purge the altar of your
hearts,<note place="margin">Pſal. 24.7.</note> cleanſe the leproſie of your
ſinne, ſanctifie your bodies and ſoules; and <hi>though Iſrael play the
harlot, yet let not Iudah ſinne,</hi> but make cleane and prepare the doores
of your tabernacles,<note place="margin">Pſal. 118.19.</note> that the King of
glorie may come in.</p>
            <p>Againe. I finde by obſeruation generally, that we are ſaid two
wayes to be cleanſed: which I may call the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer and the after labour, viz.
the inchoation and progreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion <pb n="34" facs="tcp:17075:20"/>of repentance. Man in
the former is meerly a patient, dead vnto ſinne,<note place="margin">Rom. 7.18.
2. Cor. 3.5.</note> in whom dwels no good thing; hauing no power to raiſe
himſelfe; but euen the diſpoſition of the will, which is otherwiſe
blindly led, and captiue vnto ſin, it doth proceed of him which workes all
good in all.<note place="margin">1. Cor. 12.6.</note> But in the other we are in
ſome ſort agents, <hi>cooperary Dei,</hi> liuely inſtruments to worke out
our owne ſaluation. For the former, it is no more poſſible for a man to
cleanſe him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, then to change the ſpots of a Leopard, or to waſh
white the skin of a Morian. The heart of naturall man is ſo hardened through
the deceitfulneſſe of ſinne, that ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept a more powerfull ſpirit doth
incline, and ſoften, and diſpoſe it inwardly to good, a man with as good
ſucceſſe may plow on the rocke, or ſow on the ſhoare, as by words
thinke to winne a man to repentance: for this cleanſing, it is the gift of
God, Epheſ. 2.4. and the firſt act thereof is his immediate hand; ſuch as
all the naturall eloquence and force of man cannot effect. For, as the wiſe
man ſpeaketh, <hi>Who can ſay, I haue made my owne heart cleane?</hi> Prou.
20, 19. And as that cripple which eight and thirtie yeares waited at the poole
of Betheſda, if he had not bene helped by our Sauiour, had liued and died a
cripple, becauſe he was not able to moue himſelfe into the waters, Ioh.
5.5. ſo ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept a more powerfully ſpirit doth moue, yea and compell vs into
the maine of <hi>Maries</hi> weeping water of life, we ſhould liue and die,
and be damned for want of peniten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie. <hi>Dauid</hi> therefore for the example
of all others, thus teacheth vs to turne to the God of our ſaluation:
<hi>Haue mercie vpon me, O God, according to, &amp;c.</hi> Pſal. 51.1. And
a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine, ver. 1. <hi>Waſh (thou) me throughly from mine iniquitie.</hi> And
againe, ver. 7. <hi>Purge (thou) me with byſope, &amp;c.</hi> And a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine,
ver. 10. <hi>Create in me a clane heart, O God, &amp;.</hi> And ſo the
Prophet <hi>Ieremie</hi> teacheth,<note place="margin">See Ez. 36.25</note>
               <hi>Conuert thou me, and I ſhall be conuerted, for thou art the Lord my
God,</hi> Ier. 31.18. And yet not this, but the after labour of renouation, is
the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per and moſt genuine interpretation of my text.</p>
            <pb n="35" facs="tcp:17075:20"/>
            <p>Wherein through the grace of God, we are become in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrumentall
agents to cleanſe our ſelues. And to this pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe runne all the precepts
and commandements, which call for our obedience and amendments,<note place="margin">Ezech. 18.30 Rom. 12.2. Iſa. 1.16.</note> 
               <hi>Turne you, turne
you, &amp;c. Waſh you, make you cleane, &amp;c. Faſhion not your ſelues
like vnto this world, but be yerenewed. &amp;c.</hi> And the like. Theſe
precepts we call Euangelicall, which do alwayes preſuppoſe Gods mercifull
hand to helpe, whoſe grace is preſt and readie to all that call vpon him,
more willing to giue then we to aske, and giueth more then we can deſire, yea
and is not wanting to any, except they be wanting to themſelues. And to what
end doth God lend vs eyes and eares, and hands and feete, but to ſee and
heare, and worke and walke? So his grace which is giuen vnto vs, muſt not be
idle but operatiue to all good workes, to <hi>adde to our faith vertue, to
vertue knowledge, to knowledge tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perance, &amp;c.</hi> 2. Pet.
1.5.6.—</p>
            <p>A man therefore in his renouation is not <hi>ficulnus inutile
lignum,</hi> like the image of Baal, or the ſtumpe of Dagon,<note place="margin">1. Kin. 18.17. 1. Sam. 5.4. Pſal. 13 5.15.</note> or the idols
of the Gentiles, which <hi>haue eyes and ſee not, eares and heare not,
mouthes and ſpeake not, hands, &amp;c.</hi> But as the ſicke which was
healed, muſt take vp his bed and walke;<note place="margin">Mar. 2.11.</note>
&amp; as the dumbe, the blinde, the lame, and the dead, which were reſtored
to ſpeech, and ſight, and ſtrength, and life, they ſpake, and ſaw,
and leaped, and gaue glorie to God: and as <hi>Paul,</hi> after his
conuerſion,<note place="margin">Act. 9.20.</note> muſt preſently preach the
Goſpell; ſo muſt we not ſuffer the grace of God and his good meanes to
ſleepe or be idle in vs, but we muſt ſet our hands to his plow, labour in
his vineyard, worke the ſaluation of our ſelues and others, worke (I ſay)
and that for life, euen <hi>with feare and trembling.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Phil. 2.12.</note>
            </p>
            <p>The carter driuing by the way (let me craue your ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable
patience for a familiar and homely compariſon) ſodainly his wheele chopped
into a dangerous pit, and the poore man well perceiuing the difficultie and
ſtreights to eſcape, preſently fell downe on his knees, and beſought 
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:17075:21"/>his god <hi>iupiter</hi> to come and helpe; but a voice was
retur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned vnto him, ſaying. <hi>Set thy ſhoulder to the wheele, and laſh
on thy horſes, and then I will helpe thee:</hi> euen ſo the helpe of Gods
ſauing health, is proper to the generation of See<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers, which are not
ſlacke, no nor weary of well doing, but <hi>ſeeke him with the whole
heart,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 24 6.</note> viz. with all the force and
power of the parts and powers both of bodie and mind: ſo that as it is true
in common experience, <hi>Fortes Deus adiuuat,</hi> God doth helpe and
bleſſe the endeuours of a diligent hand; ſo is it moſt true in our
purgation, Vp, and be doing,<note place="margin">Neh. 2.</note> and God will be
with you; for ſeeing God doth enable vs, we muſt ſtirre and beſtirre to
cleanſe our ſelues.</p>
            <p n="1">
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſon. </seg>1</label> 1. 
<note place="margin"> Iob 25.5.</note> Becauſe our God is moſt
pure and holy, which hath <hi>found folly in his Angels,</hi> yea <hi>and the
heauens are not cleare in his ſight,</hi> Iob 15.15. how much more is man
abhominable and filthy, which <hi>drinketh iniquitie like water?</hi> yea our
God is iealous and iuſt God,<note place="margin">Haba. 1.13.</note> whoſe
<hi>eyes cannot ſee and ſpare of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fenders. Slow to anger, but great in
power, and cannot iuſtifie the wicked,</hi> Nahum 1.3. He ſpared not the
world which ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, but ouerwhelmed all with a floud of water. He ſpared
not his Church,<note place="margin">Gen. 7.</note> the Quinteſſence of the
world: no nor his Saints,<note place="margin">Pſal. 106. iude 6. ver.</note>
the Quinteſſence of his Church: not the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels, which were in his
preſence, but threw them downe from heauen like lightning: no nor his onely
Sonne ſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding in our place,<note place="margin">Math. 27.46.</note> but he
bare the full viall of his wrath. <hi>Magna amaritudo peccati, quae tantam
amaritudinem peperit.</hi> Surely it is time that we cleanſe our ſelues,
for our God is a iealous God, to viſite the ſinnes of the fathers vpon the
children,<note place="margin">Exod. 20. Heb. 12.29.</note> to the third and
fourth generation of them that hate him.</p>
            <p n="2">
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> 2. Becauſe it is his will and pleaſure
that we ſhould be pure and holy, <hi>As obedient children</hi> (ſaith Saint
<hi>Peter</hi>) <hi>not faſhioning your ſelues to the former luſts of
your ignorance, but as he which hath called you is holy, ſo be ye holy in all
manner of conuerſation, becauſe it is written, Be ye holy, for I am
holy.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Deut. 10.17.</note> 
               <pb n="37" facs="tcp:17075:21"/>
               <hi>And if
you call him Father, which without respect of perſon iudgeth euery man
according to his worke, paſſe the time of your dwelling here in feare,</hi>
I. Pet. 1.15, 16.</p>
            <p n="3">
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> 3. Becauſe the pure in heart ſhall
onely ſtand in his pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence, to which purpoſe were all the oblations and
wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhings of the Leuiticall law, together with the differen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces and
diſtinguiſhments of the cleane and vncleane,<note place="margin">Leuit.
11.</note> in birds, and beaſts, and men alſo, to teach that no vncleane or
ſinnefull perſon ſhall ſtand in his preſence:<note place="margin">1
Cor. 15.</note> neither doth corruption in herite incorruption. For if the
queſtion be, Who ſhall aſcend into the mountaine of the Lord? or who
ſhall ſtand in his holy place? The anſwer is, <hi>Euen he that hath
innocent hands, and a pure heart,</hi> Pſal. 24. 3. 4. And <hi>Bleſſed
are the pure in heart, for they ſhall ſee God.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Math.
5.</note>
            </p>
            <p n="4">
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> 4. Becauſe the promiſes both of this
and a better life belong to them onely. <hi>Vnto the pure are all things pure,
but vnto them that are defiled and vnbeleeuing, is nothing pure, but euen their
minds and conſciences are defiled; they profeſſe that they know God, but
in workes they deny him, and are ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hominable and diſobedient, and to euery
good worke reprobate,</hi> Tit. 1.15.</p>
            <p>And for a better life. <hi>God is light</hi> (ſaith Saint
<hi>Iohn</hi>) <hi>and in him dwelleth no darkneſſe, if we ſay that we
haue fellowſhip with him, and walke in darkneſſe, we lie and do not
truely; but if we walke in the light, as he is in the light, we haue
fellowſhip one with another, and the bloud of Chriſt his Son cleanſeth vs
from all ſinne.</hi> 1. Ioh. 1. 6.7.</p>
            <p n="1">
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe. </seg>1</label> 1. The vſe of this point
is, that ſeeing in the worke of renouation, man is meerely a patient dead
vnto ſinne &amp;c. not to aſcribe the worke of renouation or corruption
vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to our ſelues, but vnto God onely. For as it was not poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible for the
Iſraelits, to paſſe through the red ſea, if God by a ſpeciall miracle
had not prepared their way and made a paſſage for them: ſo for man to
paſſe from the waies of death, to the waies of life, from the waies of
ſinne to the waies of righteouſneſſe, without the ſpeciall meditation
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:17075:22"/>and helpe of diuine grace is impoſſible. This is that
which our Sauiour ſpeaketh of, Ioh. 15.5. <hi>Without me you can do
nothing.</hi> For can we promiſe any thing more to our ſelues then
<hi>Dauid</hi> in the 119. Pſal. <hi>I will run O Lord</hi> (ſaith he)
<hi>the way of thy commandements, when thou haſt ſet my heart at
liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty?</hi> Can we run with our feete, before our hearts be prepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, or
can we run with our heart, before God hath en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larged it? Can we run the way
without the way? which is Chriſt Ieſus, away which we cannot ſee, till
our eies be enlightned? Not ſo: but when God ſhall haue opened the eies of
our vnderſtandings, then with <hi>Dauid</hi> may we ſee the wonderfull
things of Gods law. For there is <hi>gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tia praeueniens,</hi> before we can do
any good, and there muſt be <hi>gratia cooperans,</hi> to aſſiſt vs in
well doing, and <hi>gratiaper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficiens vel ſubſequens,</hi> to continue vnto
the end; ſo that we cannot perfect the worke of renouation, <hi>Niſi gratia
prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueniat, gratia cooperetur, gratiaperficiat vel ſubſequatur.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> 2. Seeing God of his mercie doth deuide
the worke of our purification with vs, and doth challenge the former to
himſelfe, it remaineth in the latter that we be not wanting to our ſelues;
but ſeeing he hath begun, conuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, cleanſed vs, let vs ſecond this
inchoation, conuerſion, purgation, by cleanſing our ſelues and working
out our owne ſaluation. For whereas formerly we were blinde, now he hath
enlightned vs; we were caſt downe, but he hath raiſed vs; we were dead in
ſinnes &amp; treſpaſſes, but he hath quickned vs, illuminating our
minds, rectifying our willes, diſpoſing our hearts from euill to good: Let
vs not be the enemies of God and our owne ſaluation, to quench the ſpirit,
but endenour our ſelues to know the good plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure of his will, for he hath
enlightned vs: to walke in his waies, for he hath raiſed vs; and by all
meanes to make our election ſure, for he doth enable vs to euery good worke.
And ſo from the property of the worke, let vs de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcend to the propriety of
the perſon.<note place="margin">The propriety of the perſon</note>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>Our ſelues]</hi> It is a worke worth the labour, to
bring <pb n="39" facs="tcp:17075:22"/>the worke of cleanſing to our owne houſe. Saint
<hi>Paule</hi> ſaith, <hi>Let a man examine himſelfe,</hi> 1. Cor. 11.<note place="margin">Prou. 18.</note> And the Wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man witneſſeth: <hi>iuſtus
primus eſt accuſator ſui. The iuſt mans iudgement beginnes at his owne
heart. Nullibi clariùs agnoſci poteſt vera iuſtitia quàm
cum de peccatis aliorum agitur; verò enim iuſtitia</hi> (<hi>vt
ait</hi> Gregorius) <hi>compaſſionem habet, falſa vero
indignationem.</hi> A righteous man is not ſooner ſeene in any thing then
in this, when compariſon is made twixt him and others: Truth and honeſty
herein are full of compaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, but falſhood and hypocriſie hatch
malice and indig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation. The eye which ſeeth all things ſeeth not it
ſelfe, viz. <hi>Per lineamrectam,</hi> but by reflection: ſo the
infirmities of others we ſee <hi>per radios directos,</hi> and they are euer
in our ſight, but our owne ſinnes we ſee <hi>per ambages &amp;
circumlo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quia,</hi> neither will we ſee them till iudgement doth force them
home to the conſcience. A wonder it is to ſee how the world is in loue with
lying vanity: <hi>Maxima pars ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minum ſtultitiae vitio laborat:</hi> who is
he amongſt vs which doth not thinke himſelfe wiſe, and cleane, and holy,
&amp; bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter then other men? <hi>Aurum &amp; opes &amp; vaſa frequens
donabit amicos, Qui velie ingenio cedere, nullus erit.</hi> That other men are
richer then themſelues ſome will cunningly grant for aduantage, to lay the
greateſt loade on the weakeſt horſe; but that men are better or more
holy, is the laſt thing that will be heard of. A ſtrange thing, that
ſinfull man who is of all creatures moſt miſerable, ſhould be of all
creatures moſt proud. Saint <hi>Paule</hi> turnes his eies into his owne
heart for the example of all others, where taking a ſtrict view, he calles
himſelfe the chiefe of ſinners: and <hi>Dauid</hi> ſpeaking of his owne
ſinnes faith, <hi>that they are euer in his ſight,</hi> Pſal. 51.3. But I
know not how men are ſicke of ſelfeloue, and the deepeneſſe of folly
doth poſſeſſe their hearts: when in the infirmities of others, they are
more then Lynceous eyes, but in their owne offences they are <hi>oculis
capti,</hi> and more blinde then Bats and Moles: In other mens ſinnes,
<hi>Polyphemus mutatur in Argum,</hi> they haue <pb n="40" facs="tcp:17075:23"/>more cies
then the Leopard hath ſpots, and not a more ſhall eſcape their cenſure;
but in their owne, <hi>Argus muta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur in Polyphemum,</hi> and they are more
blinde then <hi>Barti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maeus</hi> which knew not men from trees, neither can
they ſee beames at home. But who ſo thus raſhly wadeth into the
infirmities of others, <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>olodie fratris vel cupidine laudis ducitur:</hi>
either hatred or pride hath euermore an hand in ſuch dealing. <hi>Et qui
ſibi malus, cui bonus?</hi> and how ſhould we expect good from him to
others, which knowes not to be good vnto himſelfe? For charity firſt
purgeth her owne heart, and then in compaſſion paſſeth to the
infir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mities of others.</p>
            <p>Becauſe that euery one ſhall giue an account for his owne
ſoule,<note place="margin">Reaſon.</note> and for the meaſure of grace
which he hath receiued; other mens talents ſhall not come in our recko<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nings,
but in particular, ſo ſhall the Summons be:<note place="margin">Luk.
16.</note> 
               <hi>Redde rationem, Giue thou an account of thine owne
Stewardſhip.</hi> And <hi>What art thou then that iudgeſt another mans
ſervant, ſeeing in that thou iudgeſt another thou doeſt condemne thy
ſelfe,</hi> Rom. 2. 1. And againe, <hi>that euery ſeruant ſtandeth or
falleth to his owne Lord,</hi> Rom. 144. And in this caſe it may well be
ſaid, <hi>Who made thee a iudge or aruler ouer him? Peter</hi> therefore when
he will be ſmattering in <hi>Iohns</hi> affaires, our Sauiour anſwereth,
<hi>Quid eſt hoc tibi? What is that to thee? looke thou to thy ſelfe,
follow thoume.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ioh. 21.</note>
            </p>
            <p n="1">
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe. </seg>1</label> 1. This ſerues for the
condemnation of all hypocrites, whoſe faſhion is to wade deeply into other
mens conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences, yea and euen bloudily to goare their beſt gifts by their
mouthy and vncleane cenſures. They bind burdens heauy and grieuous to be
borne, and lay them on other mens ſhoulders.<note place="margin">Math.23.</note> but they themſelues will not touch them with the
leaſt of their fingers: Serpents, a generation of Vipers, painted Sepulchers,
who although the poyſon of Aſpes be vnder their lips, and their feete do
treade the ſteps of darkneſſe, yet theſe for a pretence of zeale and
ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſſe will throw the firſt ſtone, and purſue the infirmities 
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:17075:23"/>of their brethren with deadly hatred.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Clodius accuſat Moechos, Catilina Cethegum.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>They which are moſt in fault, for the moſt part will
ſoo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt find fault: but <hi>thou which teacheſt another, teacheſt thou
not thy ſelfe?</hi> Rom. 2. <hi>Thou that preacheſt to another, Thou
ſhalt not ſteale, doeſt thou ſteale? Or thou which ſayeſt to
ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, Thou ſhalt not commit adulterie, doeſt thou commit adul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terie?
Hypocrite, primùm ecce trabem,</hi> Matth.7.3. <hi>firſt caſt the
beame out of thine owne eye, that thou mayeſt more clearely ſee the more
that is in thy brothers eye.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe. </seg>2</label> And among all other hypocrites, it
taxeth the headlong and blind zeale of our late Separatiſts and
Anabaptiſticall ſpirits, whoſe bowels of late yeares did euen burſt
with indignation, as the bowels of <hi>Iudas</hi> guſhed out; crying out
againſt diſorders abroad, but neuer reforming their owne conſciences at
home; whereof one ſpeaketh very well, <hi>Conuenimus ad reformandam
Eccleſiam, ſed praepoſtero ordine, quiſque enim alium emendare vult,
ſeipſo neglecto:</hi> A prepoſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous kind of zeale, as of thoſe
whoſe meetings are not for the better but for the worſe, which cenſure in
ſeueritie the ſlips of others, but labour not at all to cleanſe
themſelues. The Phariſees, the fathers and predeceſſors of theſe
Secta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, they condemned our Sauiour <hi>propter peccatricem,</hi> Luk. 7.39.
they taxed his diſciples for vnwaſhen hands, Mat. 15. yea and cenſured
them for the eares of corne, Math. 12. ſo theſe ſupercilious and blind
guides, in other mens infir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mities they ſtraine at a gnat, but in their owne
they ſwal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low a camell. <hi>Qui non ſuis bonis, ſed alienis malis
ſanctimoniae laudem venantur:</hi> whoſe <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> is
<gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>: their madneſſe (I ſay) and folly is manifeſt,
becauſe not for good things (which themſelues do not,) but from euils,
which they ſpie out it others (as beſt acquainted therewith in ſecret)
hence would they gaine the name of zeale and puritie; and hereby they ſucke
no ſmall aduantage. But let me vſe once more what our Sauiour vſeth
often: <hi>Quid vides feſtucam? Hypocrite, why ſeeſt thou the mote?</hi>
Matth. 7. <hi>Et vt dicam ali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quid <pb n="42" facs="tcp:17075:24"/>mirabile:</hi> ſurely
a wonder it ſeemes to me; <hi>Qui habet trabem, videt: &amp; qui non habet
trabem, non videt.</hi> he that hath a beame in his eye, ſees: and he that
hath none, ſees not. But the reaſon is,<note place="margin">1. Cor.
13.</note> 
               <hi>Charitas non cogitat malum,</hi> A pure heart thinkes no hurt.
As when our firſt parents were innocent, they ſaw not their
nakedneſſe;<note place="margin">Gen. 3.</note> but when they had ſinned,
they ſaw, and were aſhamed: ſo a wonder it is, that their ſinnes which
are as beames in the eyes, ſhould ſo cleare their ſight, that they can
ſee motes in others.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe. </seg>3</label> It ſerueth as a ſure rule to
examine how it ſtands with vs in the caſe of humilitie: for a nearer or
truer way to know whether we be proud or humble, cannot be then this, how we
iudge our ſelues pure or holy in reſpect of others. The proud who examine
all things falſly, take this prepoſterous courſe, in comparing
themſelues with o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, they put in one ſcale the infirmities of their
brethren, and in the other their owne ſeeming righteouſneſſe,
alto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether forgetting their ſinnes, which makes them in iudg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to
iuſtifie themſelues: but the humble, beſt acquain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted with their owne
wants, other mens ſinnes being hid from them, in one ſcale put their owne
ſinnes, and in the other the good things of others; which makes them ſigh
vnder the burden of their infirmities, and ſay with the poore Publican,
<hi>God be mercifull to me a ſinner.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Moſes</hi> when his face did ſhine ſo gloriouſly, that
the people could not beare the ſplendor thereof,<note place="margin">Exod.
34.</note> onely him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe knew it nor. And the moſt dangerous
ſickneſſe which doth befall the ſoule (the bottomleſſe gulfe of
deſpaire onely excepted) is, that any ſhould thinke himſelfe pure, and
holy, and cleane, and better then other men: for they which know themſelues
ſicke, do ſeeke for helpe; but they which thinke themſelues cleane, do
liue and die in their ſinnes for want of cleanſing. But we, my brethren,
know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing our manifold and foule offences, let my text bring vs backe, whence we
are digreſſed, to cleanſe and purge our owne hearts firſt, euery one to
cleanſe one, that ſo all may <pb n="43" facs="tcp:17075:24"/>be cleanſed; cleanſed,
I ſay <hi>(from filthineſſe:)</hi> and that is the third paſſage of
the point, viz. the matter to be wrought vpon.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Filthineſſe)</hi> The matter to be wrought vpon, is
<hi>filthineſſe:</hi>
               <note place="margin">3. The mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter to be
wroughtvpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</note>where by a Synecdochicall proceſſion, is put the part
for the whole, as one figure is put for a thouſand: ſo vnder this word
<hi>filthineſſe,</hi> is comprehended ſinne in generall: and from the
very name, behold the nature of ſinne, it is called <hi>filthineſſe,</hi>
whence obſerue,</p>
            <p>Sinne is odious, as it may appeare elſewhere by the names in the
Scripture; it is called pollution, a leproſie,<note place="margin">Leuit. 20.
2. Pet. 2. 23. Ioſh. 7.</note> a contagion, the vomit of a dog, and wallowing
of a ſwine in the mire. Againe, it is called vncleanneſſe, the execrable
thing; and euery where it is ſaid to be abhomination, more loathſome then
the boiles of <hi>Iob,</hi> or the ſores of <hi>Lazarus: A menſtruous
cloth,</hi> as <hi>Iſaiah</hi> ſpeakes; <hi>The ſtoole of
wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Lam. 1.</note>as we vſe the name in the
baſeſt maner. <hi>Dauid</hi> calleth it, rottenneſſe and
putrifaction,<note place="margin">pſal. 38.</note> 
               <hi>My wounds ſtinke, and
are corrupt, &amp;c.</hi> And ſpeaking more generally of all ſinners, he
ſaith, <hi>Corrupt they are, and become abhominable.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal 14.</note> The Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet <hi>Iſaiah</hi> doth thus
decypher the nature and eſtate of ſin and ſinners, whether we ſpeake of
one ſinner, or of a ſinful nation: <hi>The whole head is ſicke, and the
whole heart is heauie: from the ſole of the foot to the head, there is
nothing whole there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in, but wounds, and ſwelling, and ſores full of
corruption: they haue not bene wrapped, nor bound vp, nor mollified with
oyle,</hi> Iſa. 1.5, 6. And the Prophet <hi>Ezechiel</hi> ſets downe the
ingen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dring of ſuch a ſpurious and beaſtly progenie, like euil and
darkneſſe, and thoſe <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>animalia,</hi> which come
not vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the view of Gods creation:<note place="margin">Ezek. 16.</note>
               <hi>Thine habitation and thy kindred</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>is of the idolatrous
Canaaniets, thy father an Amorite, and thy mother an Hittite: and in thy
natiuitie thy nauell was not cut, thou waſt not waſhed in water to ſoften
thee, thou waſt not ſalted with ſalt, nor ſwadled in clouts, but thou
waſt naked, and in thy bloud.</hi> By all which may appeare the nature of the
matter now in hand, viz. the filthineſſe and <pb n="44" facs="tcp:17075:25"/>beaſtiall pollution and vncleanneſſe of ſinne and
ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe. </seg>
               </label> Is finne ſo odious? Then ſee and know
from the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet <hi>Hoſea,</hi> the filthineſſe of a ſinfull nation,
where was <hi>no truth, nor mercie, nor knowledge of God in the land,</hi>
Hoſe.4. Theſe were not to be found there, and I would to God that we had
found what they loſt: but the heathen mans poeſie is become a true
propheſie, <hi>Terras Aſtraea reliquit, In cuius ſubiere locum
fraudeſ<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> doli<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan>.</hi> The world it is worſe and worſe, old,
cold and ſtiffe; old in iniquitie, cold in charitie, and ſtiffe in
wickedneſſe; our grandfathers were wicked, our fathers worſe then they,
and we claime the ſinnes of both by inheritance:<note place="margin">Iſa.
1.</note> 
               <hi>Ah ſinfull nation, a people la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den with iniquitie!</hi> The
filthineſſe of our age is ſuch, that, (not <hi>peragrare veſtigia
Satanae,</hi> who compaſſeth the whole earth, and walking through the
ſame, leaueth the ſpawne of vncleanneſſe in all places; nor yet to
purſue the filthi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes of this whole land,<note place="margin">Plautus.</note>
which were <hi>onus humeris impar,</hi> a burden farre too heauie for my
ſhoulders) if I ſhould but enter <hi>ionahs</hi> one dayes iourney into
this Citie and Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>urbes, and take notice of the filthy ſinnes which here are
done, it were much, and too much for my ſtammering tongue to explane, or my
troubled ſoule to ſuſtaine: wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe with me your ſelues which
ſit on the ſeate of iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, whether through <hi>ſwearing, and lying,
and killing, and ſtealing, and whoring,</hi> men breake not out, <hi>and
bloud touch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth bloud.</hi> Theſe were the foule offences of Iſrael, as the
Prophet witneſſeth, and I would to God they had bene borne and buried in
Iſrael, that we had neuer knowne them; for this famous Citie which is as the
crowne of this land,<note place="margin">Iſa. 5.</note> the compaſſe of
whoſe walls are as the vineyard of God, now through the riot of ſinne, are
in many places become <hi>Mara &amp; Amara,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ruth
1.</note> a roote of bitterneſſe, a ſinke of ſinne, a welſpring of
pollution, a ſtage of vngodlineſſe, a baite of deceitfulneſſe, and a
debarring from happineſſe. When Gods people hearkned to his voice, and
walked in <pb n="45" facs="tcp:17075:25"/>his waies, then were they bleſſed, and called
the Iſrael of God: but when they for ſooke him, and defiled them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues
with the abhominations of the heathen, God as though their ſinnes had blotted
their names out of the booke of his remembrance, he calles them <hi>Sodome and
Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morrah.</hi> Eſa. 1. Surely (brethren) Samaria by her fornica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions did
iuſtifie Sodome, and we by our hainous ſinnes do iuſtifie Samaria; for
the ſinnes of Sodome were theſe:<note place="margin">Ezech.
16.49.</note>
               <hi>Pride, fulneſſe of bread, abundance of idleneſſe, and
contempt of the poore.</hi> Ezek. 16. But conſider the filthineſſe of
ſuch a na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, where gluttony hath eaten til it hungred, and
drun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kenneſſe hath vomited till it thirſted, where pride is ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counted
the beſt faſhion, and whoredome is called a tricke of youth; where men
drinke iniquitie like water, and bind ſinnes together as it were with
cart-ropes;<note place="margin">Eſa. 5.18. 1. King. 21,</note> where as
<hi>Ahab</hi> ſold himſelfe to worke wickedneſſe in the ſight of the
Lord, ſo men as beaſts haue giuen themſelues ouer <hi>to worke all
vncleanneſſe euen with greedneſſe;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Eph.
4.19.</note> ſome like the proud Angels feathering their wings in
preſumptuous pride, ſoaring aloft til their plumes like <hi>Daedalus</hi>
his wings, melted with the fire of Gods wrath, driue them downe to the pit of
deſtruction: ſome like the couetous Caterpil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar deuouring the fruite of
the poore mans vineyard; ſome like the vnſatiable maltworme dead drunke<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in
the ſtreets; yea, here may you ſee murder and malice runne headlong to
deſtruction, monſtrous <hi>Anakims</hi> men of might,<note place="margin">Gen. 11.</note> building a Babel their owne confuſion,<note place="margin">Eſter 3.</note> enuious <hi>Hamans</hi> macera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting themſelues
for their brethrens welfare,<note place="margin">Gen. 29. 1. Sam. 25. 2. Sam 16.
Eſa. 37. Iudith. 13.</note> ſnudging <hi>Nabals</hi> and churliſh
<hi>Labans,</hi> withholding the wages of the hireling and grinding the face of
the poore; curſing <hi>She<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meies,</hi> and blackmouthed <hi>Rabſakeis,</hi>
vnnaturall Sodomites &amp; painted <hi>Iezabels,</hi> drunken
<hi>Olifernes</hi> Ioſe head and ſoule and all; and which hath brought your
ſinnes to the height, that an adulterous and an idolatrous religion hath
ſtill footing in your City and dwellings.</p>
            <p>Surely (brethren) if I ſhould totall all in iuſt account, 
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:17075:26"/>
               <hi>Dies me deficeret,</hi> this day, yea and the daies of
my mortall pilgrimage would ſooner haue an end then my labour, and therefore
I muſt be forced to vſe a peece of ciuill po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licy. Meete but with
<hi>Agag</hi> and the fatlings, the foule and crying ſinnes,<note place="margin">1. Sam. 15.</note> and the dependants may more eaſily be
re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed: And as a man that aimeth at a multitude can at one ſhoote would
only ſome few; ſo giue me leaue ſhoo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting at all filthineſſe, to
cruſh in peeces theſe two that fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low, viz. drunkenneſſe and
whoredome: which go hand in hand and haue kiſſed each other, and are not
more hai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nous then common in this City and Suburbes.</p>
            <p>And for the hatefull ſinne of drunkenneſſe, howſoeuer it
be but a fiction that <hi>Cyrces</hi> charmes turned me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to ſwine; yet ſure
I am, and wofull experience makes knowne too oft, that <hi>Bacchus</hi>
charmes, viz. ſtrong drinke it turneth men to beaſts; the ſoule of man
miraculouſly created by Gods infuſion, and infuſed by creation, lieth
drowned in the drunkards body: his body which ſhould be the temple of the
holy Ghoſt, diſtempered by exceſſiue riot, is ſuch that his ſoule
might loath to dwell therein; and his goods or poſſeſſions (be they
more or leſſe) lent for the mainte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance of himſelfe and his, are all
hoorded in the pot, and put in a bottomleſſe bag. The Lacedaemonians a
people which knew not God, by the light of nature did ſo ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>horre this
brutiſh ſinne, that their Helots, ſlaues which they bought for villanage,
they would make drunken, and bring them into the market place and expoſe them
as ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lefactours on a gibbet, that their children ſeeing their
vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleanneſſe and filthineſſe, might thereby deteſt and ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>horre that
ſwiniſh ſin. But we need not buy Helots to ſet vp as ſcarecrowes to
the world, for eueu before your doores and in your houſes may you daily ſee
theſe beaſtly Epicures: and were there not a remnant of the houſe of
Iſrael amongſt you to ſtand in the gap like <hi>Moſes &amp; Aaron</hi>
twixt the liuing and the dead, inwardly mourning and la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>menting, and as much as
in them lieth, labouring and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forming <pb n="47" facs="tcp:17075:26"/>forming theſe
foule offences, the end of this Citie would be ſudden as the fire of Sodome.
But it is written, <hi>Woe to you drunkards of Ephraim, &amp;c.</hi> Eſa. 28.
1. <hi>Woe to them that riſe vp early to follow drunk enneſſe, and ſit
till the wine inflame,</hi> Eſa. 5.11. <hi>Woe to them that are mighty to
drinke wine, and ſtrong to poure in ſtrong drinke,</hi> Eſa, 5.22.
<hi>Awake ye drunkards,</hi> faith <hi>Ioel,</hi> 1.4. <hi>and howleye that are
ſtrong to drinke.</hi> And thinke you that all theſe woes are written in
vaine? Then is our preaching vaine, and your faith alſo vaine, and this booke
of truth hath no truth in it. Hearken therefore ye men of vnderſtanding, and
you ſhall heare the drunkards doome; woe vpon woe ſhall light vpon them,
their poſterity ſhall be beggers, their eſtate conſumed, their name
ſhall rot and periſh, their bodies odious euen to them: and which is
heauier then all, their ſoules repulſed from the grace of God, ſhall
dwell with the foule and infernall ſpirits. who as their deſire was to
enter and dwell in the heard of ſwine,<note place="margin">Math. 8.</note> ſo
ſhall theſe ſwine remaine with them in chaines of darkneſſe for
euermore: And ſuch is the end of this filthineſſe.</p>
            <p>To which I may adde whoredome, like Sodome and Samria ſiſters
in impurity; for gluttony and drunkenneſſe are the gallery and way of
whoredome: <hi>Venter bene paſtus cito diſpumat ad libidinem;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gen. 19.</note> drunken <hi>Lot</hi> and inceſtuous <hi>Lot</hi>
both in one perſon, at one time; and they are ſeldome ſundred; for it is
no thing new or ſtrange, for a perſon which ſhall firſt become a
beaſt, to do after like a beaſt. It is a ſinne againſt nature, for
whereas other men ſow for an harueſt, foule fornicators and wicked
adulterers, which plow with other mens heiſers, they ſow that which they
dare not reape. But they ſhall be puniſhed both here and hereafter. Here
firſt with beggery. <hi>He that feedeth harlots waſteth his
ſubſtance,</hi> Prou. 29.3. Yea he or his poſterity ſhall be glad to
beg a peece of bread, Prou. 6.26.</p>
            <p n="2">2. With infamie, for his name and credite ſhall take
ſuch a deepe and incurable wound, that his reproch ſhall 
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:17075:27"/>neuer be done away, Prou. 6.33.</p>
            <p n="3">
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> 3. With moſt loathſome diſeaſes:
for the moſt high &amp; righteous hath appointed that they which will taſte
the ſweete of ſinne, ſhall alſo be filled with the gall of
puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment: it bringeth corruption of the bloud, diſſolution of the
ſinewes, rottennes of the marrow, aches in the ioynts, crudities in the
ſtomacke, paines in the head, defects and weakneſſe, gouts and palſies,
heauineſſe of heart and ſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging of the conſcience.</p>
            <p n="4">
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> 4. Yea and after all theſe it ſhall be
puniſhed with hel fire, for it is writen, <hi>Fornication, vncleanneſſe,
inordinate affection, &amp;c. the wrath of God remaineth on ſuch,</hi> Col.
3. 6. And a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine <hi>Whoremongers and adulterers God wil iudge,</hi> Heb.
13.4.</p>
            <p>The holy Ghoſt ioyneth a whore and a dog together, Deut. 23.18.
<hi>Thou ſhalt not bring the hire of a whore nor the price of a dog into the
houſe of God;</hi> and <hi>Ieremy</hi> compareth a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulterous beaſts to
neighing horſes. <hi>Ier.</hi> 5.8. And the wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man likens them to an oxe
going to the ſlaughter, Prou. 7.22. and calles the whore a <hi>deepe ditch
&amp; a narrow pit,</hi> Prou. 23.27. <hi>And they that enter in to her, hardly
returne againe to take hold of the way of life,</hi> Prou. 2.19. And in the
latter end when iudgement ſhall bring his ſinne to the doore of his
conſcience, he ſhall wonder at himſelfe and ſay, O now was I deceiued!
Prou. 5.12.</p>
            <p>I conclude the point with that of S. <hi>Hierome, O ignis
in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fernalis luxuria, cuius materia gula, &amp;c.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Hier.</note> Where he compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth whoredome to the infernall fire,
whoſe matter or nouriſhment are gluttony and drunkenneſſe, the flame is
<hi>feruor co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cupiſcentiae:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Hoſ. 7.4.</note> as an
ouen heated by the baker, ſo is an adulterer; the ſparkes are corrupt
ſpeeches and filthy com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munication, the ſmoke infamy and diſgrace, the
acts a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulterie, fornication, vncleanneſſe, and the end hell tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments.</p>
            <p>Drunkenneſſe and whoredome, with other the odious ſinnes of
theſe latter and dangerous times, theſe are they which haue kiſſed each
other, which go hand in hand, and <pb n="49" facs="tcp:17075:27"/>haue made a couenanc with
deſtruction, and ſworne a league with hell, for the ſubuerſion both of
Church and Commonwealth. O that I had the voice of men and an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels, to crie
againſt them: if my tongue were dipped in gal, yet could I not ſufficiently
not bitterly enough inuey a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt them. If there be any thing in death or
hell more miſerable, their tongues ſhall taſte thereof, and their bow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>els
ſhall be filled with the dregs thereof: woe vpon woe ſhall light vpon them;
and though the Sunne and Moone haue an end, yet their plagues and torments
ſhall neuer haue end. hearken, and ſtand in awe, and tremble before the
Lord your God, yemen of Iſrael: how long and how loud haue we cried againſt
theſe foule offences, and yet <hi>who hath beleeued our report? or to whom is
the arme of the Lord reuealed?</hi> Surely if our words take no deeper
im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion, it reſteth that you ſecond our words with the ſword of
iuſtice. And to the Honorable and Worſhipfull of this aſſembly be it
ſpoken, to whom God hath impar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted his own Name, (for ye are called
<hi>Gods</hi>) that you ioyne your helping hands to pull downe theſe ſhops
of iniquitie, and to ſtop and dam vp theſe ſtinking wels of
filthineſſe: for if you ſpare, and beare the ſword in vaine, the people
ſhall die in their ſinnes, but God ſhall require their bloud at your
hands. Neither may I forget to giue ſome of the worthieſt and moſt
honorable in this aſſembly their due, for the good and godly zeale they
haue ſhewed for the lord our God on this behalfe, the fame whereof hath
ſpread it ſelfe into all corners of the land, and it doth make glad the
Citie of God. I meane in puniſhing and purging theſe two forenamed vices,
to wit, drunkenneſſe and whoredome, together with the profanation of the
Sab both: may you go on like good <hi>Nehemiahs,</hi> to do worthi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in
Ephrata, and be famous in Bethlem, and the Lord ſtrengthen your hearts: and
as you labour the peace of Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruſalem, ſo let your dayes be multiplied in
peace, and bind vp their ſoules, O Lord, in the bundle of life. All that I 
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:17075:28"/>haue further to ſay to you the Magiſtracie of this
honora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Aſſembly, touching this point, is the charge of God himſelfe
to his ſeruant <hi>Ioſhua; Onely be ſtrong, and of a vali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ant courage, to
fight the Lords battels,</hi> to cut downe ſinne, to roote it out: and as you
haue begun in the Lord, ſo let your zeale abound, and be not faint hearted in
ſo good a cauſe, and behold God ſhall neither leaue you nor forſake
you, till you haue in ſome meaſure purged and cleanſed this Citie from
filthineſſe.</p>
            <p>And for you, my brethren, let my concluſion of this point turne
to you all here preſent, and you to turne to the Lord your God: <hi>o turne
you, turne you, for why will you die ye men of Iſraeli</hi> conſider your
ſinnes are great and grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uous, they are the prouocation of heauen, and
ſtrike at the maieſtie of God; ſay therefore with S. <hi>Peter,</hi> It
is enough for me that I haue ſpent the times paſt in ſurfetting and
drunkenneſſe, in couetouſnes and idleneſſe; other things, nay better
things are now required of me, namely that I liue, not after the Iuſts of the
fleſh, but after the will of God. Thus cleanſe, yea and your ſelues, yea
and cleanſe your ſelues from filthineſſe, yea and that <hi>from all
filthineſſe,</hi> and that is the fourth part and paſſage of my text,
viz. the generalitie and difficultie of the taske.<note place="margin">The
genera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litie or diffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cultie of the taske.</note>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>All filthineſſe]</hi> The Apoſtle dehorring from
ſinne, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>horteth from all ſinne; not onely from filthineſſe
<hi>indefi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nite,</hi> leſt ſinne ſhould haue a ſtarting hole, but
<hi>all filthineſſe vniuerſaliter,</hi> that no ſinne ſhould
eſcape: whence note,</p>
            <p>None muſt content themſelues with the beginnings of
mortification. For as <hi>Moſes</hi> once ſpake in the caſe of their
departure out of <hi>Aegypt, With our yong and with our olde will we go, we
will not leaue one hoofe behind:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Exod. 10 9.</note> ſo
is it euer moſt true in our departure out of the captiuitie of ſin, we
muſt not leaue one ſinne vnſearched, not an euill thought muſt be
ſpared; for <hi>whoſoeuer ſhall faile in one point of the law, is guiltie
of all,</hi> Iam. 2. 10. And againe, <hi>Whoſoeuer breaketh the leaſt of
theſe commandements, the ſame ſhall be called the leaſt 
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:17075:28"/>in the kingdome of heauen.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Act.
26.28.</note> King <hi>Agrippa</hi> therefore in reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion was like a meteor in
the aire, betwixt heauen and earth; and ſo are all that haue a deuided heart,
like the pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cture of <hi>Ianus,</hi> which looked forward and backward; euen
ſo are they halfe, and almoſt, and halting Chriſtians. But as no
defectiue perſon was to ſerue at Gods altar, no more ſhall any halting
profeſſor come in his preſence. The point is, All filthineſſe muſt
be cleanſed. Which was myſtically ſignified in the law, where
<hi>Moſes</hi> was commanded to cut the haire of the Leaper, <hi>ſupercilia
&amp; cilia,</hi> not an haire of ſinne muſt be left. The Holocauſts,
whether they were <hi>bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ues, oues,</hi> or <hi>aues,</hi> were wholy
conſumed; to teach vs, that whatſoeuer we do in Gods ſeruice, muſt be
done wholy. So Saint <hi>Paul</hi> bids vs <hi>Put on</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>the whole ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mour of God:</hi> for we muſt leaue no part
vnarmed.<note place="margin">Epheſ. 6.</note> And Chriſt faith, <hi>Take my
yoke vpon you:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mat. 12.29.</note> one would thinke that
the yoke was onely for the necke; but his yoke muſt we take on euery part.
God would haue vs powre out our hearts like water; now water leaueth no
ſauour, nor co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lour, nor droſſe behind, as other licours do: ſo muſt
we cleanſe our ſelues, euen from all appearance of finne. If we cleanſe
the Temple, let vs not leaue the Altar behind; kill both <hi>Amalek</hi> and
all his cattell; ſpare not one corrupt af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection, not the leaſt ſinne,
no not in the egge. The Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet ſpeakes of a cake baked on the harth,<note place="margin">Hoſ. 7.</note> 
               <hi>panis ſubcine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritius,</hi> baked on the one
ſide, but dough on the other; luke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warme Chriſtians, which halt twixt God
and Belial: a lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle warme, that they may ſerue God, and a little warme to
ſerue the world. But the Wiſe man ſets downe the wiſh of God, <hi>Fili
mi, &amp;c. My ſonne, giue me thy heart: non per commutationem, nec per
venditionem, ſed per donationem.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Prou. 23.</note> Some
lend their heart to God, vntil they ſee a greater ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uantage; ſome ſell
their heart to God for a reward, and God muſt ſerue them firſt. But wee
muſt giue our heart freely, and with a willing minde; our whole heart muſt
we giue, and that continually, Deut 6.5. <hi>Vae duplici <pb n="52" facs="tcp:17075:29"/>cordi,</hi> ſaith Saint <hi>Auſten. They diſſemble with a
double heart,</hi> ſaith the Pſalmiſt.<note place="margin">Pſal.
12.</note> But this I ſay, <hi>Cor diuiſum moritur,</hi> A di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uided heart
is a dead heart. <hi>Et qui diuidunt partem diabolo, &amp; partem Deo, iratus
Deus à ſua parte diſcedit, &amp; diabolus totum poſſidet:</hi>
and therefore giue God all, or thou giueſt him nothing at all, yea and do it
continually: <hi>non Deo in iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uentute, &amp; diabolo in ſenectute,</hi> like
the fooliſh Galathians, which began in the ſpirit,<note place="margin">Gal.
3.</note> but would end in the fleſh. In a word, we may giue our knowledge to
the ignorant, our goods to the poore, our taxes to <hi>Ceeſar,</hi> but our
hearts on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to God, freely and wholy.</p>
            <p>Becauſe that as one flie corrupteth the whole boxe of
ointment,<note place="margin">Reaſon.</note> ſo one ſinne makes vs liable
to condemnation. The Apoſtle therefore ſpeakes of ſinne in
ſingular,<note place="margin">Rom. 6.23.</note> 
               <hi>Stipen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dium peccati, The
wages of ſinne,</hi> not of many, but of any ſin <hi>is death.</hi> And if
we ſhould ſuffer ſo many deaths as we haue committed ſinnes, yet were
Gods iudgements iuſt and right. A ſhip is endangered by one leake in the
ſide, and a citie ſurpriſed by one breach in the wall; and a fowler
cat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheth the bird as well by one part as the whole bodie. So ſinne is like
leauen, and a little leauen leaueneth the whole lumpe:<note place="margin">Gal.
5.9. 2. King. 2.</note> one Coloquintida brought death into the pot, and one
dead worke of darkneſſe deſtroyeth the ſoule.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe. </seg>
               </label> It ſerueth to condemne the halting
profeſſion of our diſſembling age; wherein many will be content to
leaue ſome ſinnes,<note place="margin">1. Sam. 1 5.9.</note> but keepe
others: as <hi>Saul</hi> ſpared <hi>Agag</hi> and the fatlings; and as
<hi>Herod</hi> ſpared his luſt and vnlawfull marriage.<note place="margin">Mat. 6.12.</note> 
               <hi>Ananias</hi> and <hi>Saphira</hi> were
willing to bring a part to the Apoſtles, but they were loth to bring all. The
yong man in the Goſpel would follow Chriſt, but he was loth to <hi>ſell
all;</hi> ſo that this word <hi>(all)</hi> marres all. Euery man would go to
heauen with his darling. The couetous would go with his gold; the vicious with
his harlots; the ambitious with his braue attire, &amp;c. But touch the world
in theſe their profitable, pleaſant, darling and boſome ſinnes, and you
ſhall heare men ſpeake as in the houſe of <hi>Rimmon,</hi> like
<hi>Naa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man</hi> 
               <pb n="53" facs="tcp:17075:29"/>the Aſſyrian, <hi>God be mercifull to
me in this.</hi>
               <note place="margin">2. King. 5.</note> Preach to the vſurer or
oppreſſour, <hi>That he which doth not prouide for his owne familie is
worſe then an infidel,</hi> or againſt prodigality or ſuretiſhip, and
your word ſhall be as the firſt and latter raine, and ſinke deepe into
his romembrance; but turne him to Pſal. 15. where no vſurer ſhall reſt
in Gods holy hill. or 1. Cor 6. where no extortioner ſhall enter into the
kingdome of heauen; or to Saint <hi>Matthew</hi> concerning workes of mercie,
or to Saint <hi>Luke</hi> againſt couetouſneſſe: and you ſhall finde
him eared like the deafe adder, and his heart harder then the nether
milſtone, But it is written, <hi>If thy right eye offend thee,</hi> that
is,<note place="margin">Math. 5.</note> if thy ſinne be as deare vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to thee as
the apple of thine eye, yet pull it out, and let not thine eye ſpare it;
<hi>or if thy right hand offend thee,</hi> that is, if thy ſinne be as
profitable and commodious as thy hand whereby thou getteſt thy liuing, yet
cut it off and caſt it from thee: or if thy foote offend thee to cauſe thee
to ſin, that is, if thy ſinne be ſo neceſſary as thy foote wherewith
thou beareſt thy ſelfe, yet ſpare it not: <hi>For it is better to enter
into the kingdome of God, blinde, and lame, and maimed, then otherwiſe to be
caſt into hellfire.</hi> For one ſinne in the ſoule is like a ſerpent
in the boſome, caſt it from you, or it will ſting you to death: and as
<hi>Dalila</hi> neuer left fawning and flattering <hi>Sampſon</hi> till ſhe
made him a mill horſe to the Philiſtimes; ſo your ſinne if you truſt
it, will betray you to the diuel, and he will ſend you with ſuch a griſt
to grinde, that you ſhall pay your ſoule for the tole. As therefore it is
ſaid of <hi>Iob.</hi> 1. that he was <hi>integer &amp; rectus,</hi> and ſo
muſt we be, <hi>integri,</hi> ſound and not hollow, and <hi>recti,</hi>
ſtraight and not crooked; and ſo are all good men, and euery good worke
both within and without. And to this purpoſe ought we to ſet God alwaies
before our eies:<note place="margin">1. 2. 3. 4. Eph. 6.6.</note> and to think
vpon iudgement and our account: and to conſider that eye ſeruice is nothing
pleaſing to God: and to remember that as Chriſt gaue his heart bloud for
vs, ſo as (Saint <hi>Ber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nard</hi> ſaith) <hi>Iuſtè cor noſtrum
vendicat quiſuum pro nobis dedit;</hi> 
               <pb n="54" facs="tcp:17075:30"/>He (I ſay) hath
redeemed vs, and therefore ought we to cleanſe our hearts from all ſinne,
and giue all to his ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uice. This is the point which I aime at, viz. the
triall of out integrity, when a man can ſay with good conſcience, as
Pſal. 139. <hi>Try me O God, and know my heart, proue me and knew my
thoughts, and conſider if there be any way of wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe in me;</hi> or
at the leaſt as it is Pſal. 7.3. <hi>if there be any wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kedneſſe in my
hands.</hi> Surely (brethren) I ſay to you that are the elect of God, Let vs
thus examine our owne hearts vpon our beds,<note place="margin">Pſal. 4.</note>
and in our chambers ſecretly, and cleanſe our ſelues from all
filthineſſe: All filthineſſe (I ſay) both of the fleſh and
ſpirit, which is the laſt paſſage of this point, viz. The ſpeciality
of the parts and powers infected.</p>
            <p n="5">5.<note place="margin">5. The ſpeciality of the parts and
powers infected.</note> 
               <hi>Of the fleſh and ſpirit]</hi> There was a law
in Rome, <hi>De purgandis fontibus,</hi> and it holds good in Scripture, where
we muſt purge our hearts, which is <hi>fons vitoa, tam naturalis quàm
ſpiritualis;</hi> and in purging of our heart we muſt cleanſe our bodies,
yea and our ſoules alſo from all filthi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of the fleſh and
ſpirit: whence note,</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Doct. </seg>
               </label> We muſt mortifie our bodies, and
mortifie our ſoules, and ſo giue the whole to Gods ſeruice, Rom. 12.1.
<hi>I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeech you (brethren) by the mercies God that you giue vp your bodies
and ſoules a liuing ſacrifice, &amp;c.</hi> In ſtead of the bodies of
dead beaſts, we muſt giue our bodies a liuing ſacrifice, and in ſtead
of the bloud of beaſts which was a ſhadow, and pleaſed not God of it
ſelfe, we muſt giue vp the ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptable ſacrifice of the ſoule; and this
is <hi>iuge ſacrificium,</hi> viz. a perpetuall mortifying of the will,
reaſon, affections and members: <hi>Atque haec obedientia non poteſt plus
dare, dedit enim ſe.</hi> And therefore muſt we mortifie both, that we may
ſanctifie him both in body and ſoule; not onely ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in the outward
organe of ſpeech: <hi>My ſoule praiſe thou the Lord,</hi> Pſal, 103.1.
but body and ſoule, fleſh and ſpirit, muſt ioyne their forces as well
tuned Cymbals, <hi>Praiſe thou the Lord ô my ſoule, &amp; al that is
within me, praiſe his holy name.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſon. </seg>
               </label> Becauſe God created both. <hi>He
hath made vs and not we <pb n="55" facs="tcp:17075:30"/>our ſelues,</hi> Pſal. 100. And
therefore are we due vnto his ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uice. <hi>Totum fecit</hi> (ſaith
<hi>Auguſtine</hi>) &amp; <hi>totum exigit:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Auguſt.</note> He made all, and therefore will he haue all, not
a peece of thy heart, nor a roome in the heart, but thy whole heart; not a
member of thy body or ſome parts of thy body, but the whole man: <hi>Redde
Caeſari qua Caeſaris ſunt;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Math. 22, 21.</note>
giue him I ſay the whole, for it is due vnto him. The whole body morti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied
from ſinne, and thy whole heart purged by faith ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thed in the bloud of the
Lambe, and cleanſed by the fire of the ſpirit: Not an old heart, nor a
corrupt heart, but a new heart and a new ſpirit, for which the Prophet
<hi>Dauid</hi> begged: <hi>Create in me a new heart O Lord, and renew a right
ſpirit within me,</hi> Pſal. 51.10.</p>
            <p n="1">
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe. </seg>1</label> 1. This teacheth vs, that
ſinne is there to be rooted our where it had beginning, which is from the
heart; <hi>For out of the heart proceede thefts, adulteries, murders, &amp;c.
Out of the abundance of the heart the tongue ſpeaketh,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Math. 15 19. Math. 12.34.</note> the hand wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>k<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>th, the foote walketh; and therefore
ſaith <hi>Ieremy.</hi> 4. <hi>Waſh thine heart (ô Ieruſalem) from
all wickedneſſe.</hi> The Prophet findeth not fault ſo much that euill
thoughts came in, but that they ſtayed there: A fooliſh heart therefore is
com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared to the axle tree in the wheele, which continually turneth, and yet
ſtaieth in the wheele: ſo the thoughts of an euill heart are not expelled
but turned ouer; therefore the onely meanes to cleanſe our bodies is to
cleanſe our hearts; and the onely meanes to cleanſe our hearts, is to let
the feare of God keepe the doore of our hearts. Let vs therefore conſider,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/>
               <hi>Quid amiſimus,</hi> viz. our owne free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome.
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/>
               <hi>Cui offendimus,</hi> God our maker; <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/>
               <hi>Et quò tendimus,</hi>to hell and damnation. Let vs cleanſe
therefore our fleſh and ſpirit, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/>
               <hi>frequentieiectione</hi> of euill thoughts receiued,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/>
               <hi>di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligenti euitatione</hi> of all enticements,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/>
               <hi>&amp; ſedula repreſſione</hi> of all carnall
concupiſcence. And we muſt do it ſpeedily; for if a garment be ſtained
it will eaſily be cleanſed, if it be waſhed preſently, a coale will not
burne if thou hold it not too long: therefore we ſhould learne wiſedome of
the <pb n="56" facs="tcp:17075:31"/>worldly, who in their generation are wiſer then the
chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of light; who if any flouds or inundations are likely to endanger
their lands or houſes, they vſe all meanes to turne the current of the
ſtreames another way: and ſo ſhould we turne the current of our fleſh
and ſpirit moo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing vs to euill, <hi>orando, meditando, laborando, ſemper
aliquid bone operando, it a vt diabolus cum veniat, iuuentat nos ſemper
occupatos:</hi> Either by thinking vpon the paſſion of Chriſt, or of the
ioyes of heauen, or of the paines of hell, or in the performance of the duties
of our callings, or in powring out our prayers vnto God, alwaies labouring
good, and theſe will turne the current of our hearts another way.</p>
            <p n="2">
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> 2. If we muſt cleanſe our bodies and
ſoules, and giue both to Gods ſeruice, what ſhall I ſay them of the
Papiſts who will ſerue the Lord onely in their bodily exerciſes? their
beade-prayers, &amp; worſhip in an vnknown tong, their knocking, kneeling,
croſſing, creeping, crouching, tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nings, lifting vp and letting downe
their blockiſh Roode, and kiſſing their painted Paxe, their holy water
ſprinkling, their going on pilgrimage bare footed and bare legged, their
whipping themſelues on Saints eues, and ſuch their ſuperſtitious
fooleries, are meerely outward exerciſes, which as concerning the fleſh
haue a ſhew of holineſſe in voluntary religion and not ſparing of the
fleſh, but haue no ſuch power, Coloſ. 2.23. <hi>For bodily exerciſe
profiteth no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing.</hi> 1. Tim. 4.8.</p>
            <p n="3">3<note place="margin">3. Eſa. 29.13.</note> With theſe may
I ranke the hypocrits of our times which ſerue the Lord in ſhew and not in
truth, which draw neare to God with their mouthes, but their hearts are farre
from him: ſuch are the knee-praiers and lip-la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours of our time-ſeruing
hearers, which outwardly pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe Chriſt, but inwardly <hi>Belial;</hi>
Chriſtians onely in name, Saints onely in ſhew: of which Saint
<hi>Bernard</hi> ſpeakes. <hi>Multi ſunt oues habitu, vulpes actu,
crudelitate lupi.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Bernard.</note> Sheepe in ſhew,
foxes in deede, and wolues in cruelty: for an hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocrite hath, <hi>vulpem in
cerebro, miluum in manu, &amp; lupum in <pb n="57" facs="tcp:17075:31"/>corde;</hi> a foxe
in his braine, a kite in his hand, and a wolfe in his heart. A foxe in his
braine, ſubtill and crafty to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſnare, and then he hath <hi>miluum in
manu,</hi> a kite in his fiſt to hold faſt; and when he hath caught hold,
he hath <hi>lupum in corde,</hi> a wolfe in his heart to deuoure. And therefore
our Sauiour Chriſt ſaith, <hi>Beware of falſe Prophets which come to you
in ſheepes cloathing, but inwardly are rauening wolues:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Math. 7.16.17</note>which in painted boxes hide deadly poyſons,
in beautifull Sepulchers rotten bones, and vnder <hi>Iezabels</hi> painted face
a whores behauiour; and therefore our Sauiour calleth them ſerpents, and
viperous ſerpents, O ye viperous ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pents, ye generation of vipers,
<hi>how ſhall you eſcape the dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation to come?</hi> Math. 23.33. And to
ſhew the certaintie of their damnation, beſide the manifold woes which
Chriſt denounceth againſt them, it is ſaid, that wicked men ſhall
<hi>haue their portion with hypocrites;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Math.
24.51.</note> to ſhew that the condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation of hypocrites is moſt ſurely
ſealed. Let me there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore vſe that counſell of <hi>Chryſoſtome,
Hypocrita, aut eſto quod appares, aut appare quodes,</hi> Either be as thou
ſeemeſt, or appeare as thou art: for <hi>ſimulata ſanctitas eſt
duplex ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quitas,</hi> Counterfet pietie is double impietie; firſt becauſe
it is impietie. and then becauſe it is counterfet, making truth falſhood,
and God a liar. But as it is ſaid,<note place="margin">Rom. 2.</note> 
               <hi>Non
audi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tores ſed factores legis; not the hearers of the law, but the doers of
the law ſhall be iuſtified.</hi> So of religion, <hi>Non eandem
profi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentes, ſed eidem obedientes:</hi> not profeſſors, but performers
ſhall be glorified. Let vs not therefore be like the fig tree which our
Sauiour curſed, that had leaues in abundance,<note place="margin">Math.
21.</note> but no fruite at all: for it is not the lifting vp of our eyes, nor
the knocking of our breaſts, nor the holding vp of our hands which ſhall
ſtand vs in ſtead in the latter day; but the wounded ſoule, the
ſinceritie of the heart,<note place="margin">Pſal. 5 1.17.</note> the
contrite ſpirit ioyned with our outward obſeruance and obedience which
ſhal adminiſter true ioy in the latter end. And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore let vs, as the
elect of God, holy and beloued, let vs (I ſay) profeſſe with our mouthes,
and practiſe with our <pb n="58" facs="tcp:17075:32"/>liues; let vs ſing in voice and
with the ſpirit alſo, let vs re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent in life and ſow in teares; let vs
cleanſe the fleſh that we may be mortified, and cleanſe our ſpirit,
ſo ſhall we be glorified. And of the former generall part of my text, viz.
the worke of mortification, thus farre. Now followeth the other, viz.
viuification. <hi>And grow vp, &amp;c.</hi> Where before we further paſſe,
conſider with me a little this copulatiue particle <hi>(And.)</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>And]</hi> I his word ſtandeth as a bridge in the
paſſages of my text, may it pleaſe you to ſtand vpon it a little, and
looke both wayes, you ſhall obſerue the Apoſtles order; whoſe order is,
firſt dehorting from ſinne, and then ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>horting to holineſſe: firſt
killing the old man with the fil thy workes of darkneſſe, and then
raiſing the new man, which according to God is created in holineſſe and
righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſſe. Firſt <hi>Cleanſe your ſelues from all
filthineſſe of the fleſh and ſpirit;</hi> and then <hi>grow vp to full
holineſſe in the feare of God;</hi> whence obſerue.</p>
            <p>Sinne muſt be rooted out before holineſſe can be plan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted
in.<note place="margin">Doctr.</note> For <hi>Sarah</hi> can haue no contented
peace ſo long as there is an <hi>Hagar</hi> in the houſe or family; and
therefore ſaith the Scripture, <hi>Caſt out the bond woman,</hi> viz.
ſinne, and let not thine eye ſpare her, though ſhe hath had fauour of the
fleſh and ſpirit, yet make a cleane riddance, and leaue not a brat or rag
of her behind.<note place="margin">Pſal. 34. 14. Iſa. 1.</note> Firſt
<hi>ceaſſe to do euill</hi> (ſaith <hi>Dauid)</hi> then <hi>learne to do
well. Eſchue euill</hi> (ſaith <hi>Iſaiah) and</hi> then <hi>do
good.</hi> Firſt we muſt die vnto ſinne and then liue vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to
righteouſneſſe; for <hi>viuendo morimur, &amp; moriendo viui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus,</hi> in
liuing we muſt die, and dying we ſhall for euer hue.<note place="margin">Ambroſe.</note> And therefore Saint <hi>Ambroſe</hi> inuerteth
that ſaying of the preacher, Eccleſ. 2. <hi>There is a time to line, and a
time to die:</hi> nay rather (ſaith he) there is time to die, and a time to
liue.<note place="margin">Leo.</note> 
               <hi>Et melius eſt mori Chriſto</hi>
(ſaith <hi>Leo</hi>) <hi>qui mortuos e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rigit, qràm viuere diabolo
quiſtantes deprimit:</hi> Better to die to Chriſt which raiſeth the dead,
then to liue in ſinne which deſtroyes the liuing.</p>
            <pb n="59" facs="tcp:17075:32"/>
            <p n="1">1.<note place="margin">Reaſon 1. Math. 9.17.</note> 
               <hi>Ab
incommodo; becauſe no man putteth new wine into old veſſels, for the
veſſels breake, and the wine is loſt, but new wine muſt be put into new
veſſels, that both may be preſerued;</hi> no more can the word of Gods
grace take effect, or newneſſe of life be begun in the old veſſels of
ſinne.<note place="margin">Luk 8.14.</note> For as the thornie cares of the
world do choake the word; ſo to the wicked Iew and Grecian, and man of
ſinne, the grace of God is a ſtumbling blocke, blindneſſe and
fooliſhneſſe; and to of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer his promiſed graces and fauours vnto
ſuch, is but to caſt pearles before ſwine, or to giue holy things vnto
dogges.</p>
            <p n="2">2.<note place="margin">2. 2. Cor. 6.15.</note> 
               <hi>Ab
impoſſibili:</hi> becauſe two contraries cannot at once agree in one
ſubiect: and <hi>What fellowſhip hath light with darkneſſe, or Chriſt
with Belial?</hi> The altar of the heart there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore muſt firſt be
cleanſed, before the ſacrifice of righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe be offered; the
vnfruitfull workes of darkneſſe muſt be purged out, before that
holineſſe can be plan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted in.<note place="margin">Vſe.</note>
            </p>
            <p>This ſerues for the condemnation of thoſe which think to
attaine grace ſufficient, yea and glorie alſo, although they cleanſe not
themſelues from ſinne: but theſe are thoſe fooliſh builders which
would build the houſe of holineſſe without a foundation, and ioyne the
ſame together with the vntempered morter of iniquitie; but the grace of God
pertaines not to ſuch, neither haue they part in the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes: yea in this
ſtate of ſinne, they are altogether exclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded from the kingdome; for it is
written euen of the beſt, which doth otherwiſe beſt approue
himſelfe,<note place="margin">Luk. 13.3.</note> 
               <hi>Except you repent, you
ſhall all periſh.</hi> So that ſinne ſo long as it reignes or remaines
in a man not repented of, it is the barre of Gods grace and our owne
ſaluation. We reade of him which came to offer his gift,<note place="margin">Mat. 5.23.</note> that he was ſent backe firſt to purge the
altar of his heart from the leauen of malice and ſtrife. And it is moſt
true of any perſon, ſo long as he con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinues in any ſinne not repented of
and caſt out, his ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uice is not acceptable, but his prayers are
abhominable. <pb n="60" facs="tcp:17075:33"/>Nay ſuppoſe further, that he hath done
many good works (as the wicked ſhall one day p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eade, <hi>In thy name haue we propheſied, and through
thy name caſt out diuels,)</hi> yet if he commit iniquitie, <hi>all his
righteouſneſſe that he hath done, ſhall not be mentioned,</hi> Ezech.
18.24. <hi>but in his tranſgreſſion that he hath committed, and in the
ſinne that he hath ſinned he ſhall die.</hi> In the tranſition of the
points of my text therefore, let me exhort you in the name of Chriſt, and the
words of the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Ghoſt, as it is written, Ezech. 18.30. <hi>Returne
therefore, and cauſe others to turne from all your tranſgreſſions, and
ſo ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quitie ſhall not be your deſtruction: caſt away all your
tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſions whereby you haue tranſgreſſed, and make you a new
heart and a new ſpirit, that holineſſe may be planted in: for why will
you die, O houſe of Iſrael?</hi> It followeth,</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Grow vp to full holineſſe in the feare of God.]</hi> Which
part of the concluſion, I haue formerly viewed vnder three heads.</p>
            <list>
               <item>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> 1. The growth <hi>(Growvp)</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> 2. The perfection <hi>(to fall
holineſſe.)</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> 3. The meaſure or rule to maintaine and
preſerue godli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, viz. <hi>(in the feare of God.)</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>Grow vp.]</hi> After mortification, hauing once
cleanſed our ſelues, we muſt not ſtay there, as Iſrael at the foote
of the hill,<note place="margin">Exod. 19.</note> but with <hi>Moſes</hi>
aſcend into the mount of God, and increaſe in holineſſe: whence
note,</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Doctr. </seg>
               </label> Such as are mortified to ſinne, muſt
riſe a gaine: as impes tranſplanted out of the common of this world into
the E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den of God.<note place="margin">Pſal. 1.</note> So Saint <hi>Peter</hi>
wils to grow vp, 2. Pet. 3.18. <hi>But grow in grace and knowledge of our Lord
Ieſus Chriſt.</hi> The poeſie of <hi>Apelles,</hi> was, <hi>Nulla dies
ſine linea:</hi> and I ſubſcribe, <hi>Nullalinea ſine linea:</hi> No
day without a line, and no line ſeene or read, without ſome fruite.
<hi>Titus</hi> the Emperour was wont to ſay of a day that paſſed him
without ſome good, <hi>Perdidi diem;</hi> to teach vs, that all time is not
time to vs, which is not lent to this ſeruice. In the old law, the ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uant
which after ſeuen yeares ſeruice would abide with his maiſter,<note place="margin">Exod.
21.6.</note> he was to bore a hole through his eare, and <pb n="61" facs="tcp:17075:33"/>naile him to the poſt of his doore. As the maiſter dealt with his
ſeruant, ſo muſt we deale with our ſelues, viz. bore an hole through
(not our eare, but) our heart, and naile that to the houſe of holineſſe.
God in the beginning ſaith, <hi>The euening and the morning was the firſt
day,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gen. 1.</note> and ſo of the reſt; but of the
Sabboth there is no mention made either of morning or euening; to teach that
our ſeruice to God muſt be without euening, viz. without ending; and ſo
muſt be our growth in godlineſſe. The kingdome of God is compared to a
graine of muſtard-ſeed, Math. 13. which is firſt an herbe, then the
greateſt of herbes, then a tree, and laſtly hath boughes and branches,
wherein the fowles of heauen make their neaſts. And ſo the kingdome of
hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen is oft compared to things increaſing, to teach our growth and
progreſſe in weldoing, if we haue faith to confirme it, <hi>(Lord I
beleeue, helpe my vnbeleefe;)</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mar. 9.24. Luk. 7.47.
Pſal. 129.139.</note> if loue to increaſe it, <hi>(Many ſinnes are
forgiuen her for ſhe loued much:)</hi> if zeale to enkindle it <hi>(The zeale
of thy houſe hath euen eaten me vp.)</hi> And as God hath begun and continued
a chaine of his high fauours towards vs, in predeſtinating, calling,<note place="margin">Rom. 8.30.</note> iuſtifying, ſanctifying, and glorifying his
Church: ſo let vs encounter his loue with all diligence, ioyning to our
<hi>vertue faith. to faith knowledge, to knowledge temperance, to temperance
patience, to patience godlineſſe, to godlineſſe brother<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
kindneſſe, to brotherly kindneſſe loue.</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 Pet.
1.5.6.</note> And thus by ioyning together the linkes of this golden chaine of
his graces, we muſt grow vp from grace to grace.</p>
            <p n="1">
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſon. </seg>
               </label> 1. Becauſe we are as new borne
babes, and as a building begun. <hi>As new borne babes deſire the ſincere
milke of the word that you may grow thereby,</hi> 1 Pet. 2.2. Now as babes
which are not fed do periſh, and as a building begun and not fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed, comes
to nothing; it is euen ſo in the nurſing and building of the inward
man.</p>
            <p n="2">
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> 2. Becauſe we haue taſted of the good
word of God, and the powers of the world to come, and therefore if we proceede
not in well doing, <hi>we crucifie the Lord anew vnto <pb n="62" facs="tcp:17075:34"/>our
ſelues, and make a mocke of his fauours.</hi> Heb. 6.6.</p>
            <p n="1">
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe. </seg>1</label> 1. This ſerueth for the
examination and condemnation of thoſe which the world calls harmeleſſe
men, who haue ſet vp their pride in this: viz. To do no harme: But he which
proceeds no further, is as one that hauing a long iourney to trauell, doth
pitch downe his reſt in the midſt of the way: but as the Iſraelits that
ſtaied and died in the deſert, they ſaw not the land of Canaan, no more
ſhall any ſuch ſee the ſaluation of God; for the breach of the law is
not onely commiſſion, but omiſſion, and <hi>the wages of ſinne is
death,</hi> and omiſſion of duty is commiſſion of iniquitie. This I
ſay, that he which endeuoureth an harmeleſſe life, to deale vprightly and
iuſtly, and not to defraud or wrong his brother, this man is in the way to
the king dome of heauen; but if thou wilt be perfect, <hi>Hoc vnum
re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtat;</hi> do well, and endeauour thy ſelfe to euery good work: and thus
we muſt grow in grace that we may attaine to ful holineſſe: and that is
the perfection of our worke, and the part that now enſueth.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>To full holineſſe]</hi> The Apoſtle would haue vs like
the wiſe builder in the Goſpel, who gaue not ouer his worke till he
brought it to perfection: we muſt grow, to <hi>[full ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſſe]</hi>
from whence obſerue.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> No man muſt content himſelfe with the
beginnings of viuification, but endeauour perfection. The Iſraelits ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thered
Manna euery day but vpon the Saboath day, to teach vs and teach the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, that
vntil that euerlaſting Saboath of reſt, where we ſhall be glorified
bodies and ſoules, we muſt neuer ſtand ſtill in our Chriſtian growth.
But as the waters ſpoken of in <hi>Ezechiel,</hi> grew vp by degrees, firſt
to the ankles, then to the knees, then to the loynes, and laſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to the
head; and as the wheate our Sauiour ſpoke of, grew vp by degrees, firſt
there was the blade, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> came the ſtalke, after that the full corne, but
laſtly came the har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueſt: euen ſo like that water we muſt grow higher
and higher til we come to our head Chriſt, and like that corne 
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:17075:34"/>riper and riper vntill the end of the world when the Lord
ſhall winnow the chaffe from the wheate, the wheate he ſhall receiue into
his garner, but the chaffe to be burnt vp with vnquenchable fire. Thus we
muſt grow vnto full holineſſe.<note place="margin">Mat. 2.9.</note> For as
the ſtarre which directed the wiſe men in their ſearch, ceaſſed not
till it came to the place where Chriſt was, and there it ſtayed; ſo
muſt we not ſtay in the courſe of holineſſe till we come to heauen
where God is. And as the kine of the Philiſtims which drew the Arke of God,
1. <hi>Sam.</hi> 6. though they were milch and had calues at home, the one to
weaken them, the other to withdraw them, yet without turning to the right hand
or left, they kept on their way till they came to Bethſhemeſh: ſo ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing
once ioyned our ſelues to the yoake of Chriſt, and bearing the arke of his
law vpon our ſhoulders in the way of a vertuous life, though we haue many
hindrances, wordly allurements, the diuels temptations, and our owne ſinfull
prouocations, yet muſt we keepe on the way of ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſſe to perfection:
and ſo the apoſtle exhorteth, Phil. <hi>3. Let vs as many as be perfect be
thus mindid;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Luk. 1.</note> like <hi>Zachary</hi> and
<hi>Elizabeth,</hi> of whom Saint <hi>Luke</hi> reporteth that they were both
righteous befor God, walking in all the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandements and iuſtifications of
the Lord without re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buke: that is, without iuſt exception to be taken
againſt them. yet to dreame of an abſolute and Angelicall per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection in a
mortall man, was the errour of the Pelagian heretikes: but our perfection is in
part, not wholly, in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect, not abſolute: or perfect we may be ſaid
towards men, but not in relation to God. There is alſo a perfection by way of
compariſon with others; and ſo, <hi>optimus ille eſt qui minimis
vrgetur;</hi> he is the moſt perfect man which hath the feweſt faults. Yea
and further there is a perfection of holineſſe, <hi>ſecundùm huius
vitae modum,</hi> according to the meaſure and proportion of this life; and
this perfection euery good man muſt haue. Saint <hi>Paule</hi> deſcribes it
thus, Phil. 3.3. <hi>I account not my ſelfe that I haue attained perfection, 
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:17075:35"/>but one thing I do, I forget that which is behind, and
endeauour my ſelfe to that which is before, and follow hard toward the marke,
for the price of the high calling of God in Chriſt Ieſus:</hi> So that this
is the point. We muſt reſolue, endeauour, contend, and ſtriue for
perfection as for a prize, euer be adding grace, till we are in ſome ſort
according to the capacity of our humane nature perfect men in Chriſt Ie
ſus: and to this our Sauiour exhorts. <hi>Beye perfect as your heauenly
Father is perfect. Math.</hi> 5.48. neither muſt we de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſt till we come
to full holineſſe.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſon. </seg>
               </label> Becauſe <hi>non progreds eſt
regredi:</hi> and our life is like the tumbling of a bowle vp an high hil,
which if it be throwne part of the way, or halfe or more, it returneth againe;
but if it be throwne to the top, there it reſteth: ſo the hauen of
holineſſe it is <hi>Olympus</hi> an high hill, which we muſt climbe to
the top; for to ſticke or ſtay in the midſt is but loſt la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour. Againe
our life is as a Boate rowed againſt the ſtreame, where if the rowers
ſtay, it goeth backeward of it ſelfe: ſo in the worke of holineſſe we
ſtriue againſt the ſtreame of our affections, and if we deſiſt or be
ſlacke in weldoing, they draw vs backe to cuill.</p>
            <p n="1">
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe. </seg>1</label> 1. To teach vs the danger of
apoſtacy as of thoſe which fall from their holineſſe; which begin with
<hi>Peter</hi> and end with <hi>Iudas,</hi> hauing entred the couenant of grace
they fall away like vntimely fruites, trees that are twiſe dead and plucked
vp by the roots,<note place="margin">Iude v.12.</note> whoſe end is to be
burned; which turne to their old bias of iniquitie as the dog to his vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mite,
and as the ſow that is waſhed to her wallowing in the mire.<note place="margin">Gen. 19.29.</note> 
               <hi>Lots</hi> wife for this we know was turned
into a pillar of ſalt, and ſet vp in example to ſeaſon others; and that
we forget not, our Sauiour ſets a <hi>memento</hi> before her name:
<hi>Remember Lots wife. Luk.</hi> 17. 31. for as it was with her,
<hi>Vbireſpexit ibiremanſit,</hi> where ſhe looked backe there ſhe
ſtood: ſo no man putting his hand to the plough of holineſſe and
looketh backe, is fit for the kingdome of God. Saint <hi>Paul</hi> giueth the
reaſon, which who ſo conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dereth <pb n="65" facs="tcp:17075:35"/>in heart, it will
cauſe the heart-ſtrings to ake, and the bones to quake for feare. <hi>It is
impoſſible</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>that they which were once enlightened, and
haue taſted of the hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenly gift, and were made partakers of the holy
Ghoſt, and haue taſted of the good word of God, and the powers of the world
to come, if they fall away, that they ſhould be renewed againe by
re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance.</hi> Heb. 6.4.5. <hi>For they after they haue eſcaped the fil.
thineſſe of the world</hi> (ſaith Saint <hi>Peter,</hi> 2. Pet. 2.20.)
<hi>through the knowledge of the Lord leſus Chriſt, and are againe
intan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gled therein, and ouercome, the latter end is worſe then the
be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning: for it had bene better for them not to haue knowne the way of
righteouſneſſe, then after they haue knowne it, to turne from the holy
commandement giuen vnto them.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> 2. It ſerueth to condemne our ſtanding
ſtill, our dulneſſe and ſlackneſſe in the purſuite of
holineſſe. A miſerie it is to ſee how the men of this our age are
fallen from their ſtedfaſtneſſe, from zeale to coldneſſe. For where
is that diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipline in manners, zeale to the word, hunger and thirſt after
righteouſneſſe, which doth become and adorne the Goſpell of Chriſt?
May I not ſpeake in generall, and your conſciences beare me
witneſſe,<note place="margin">Reu 2.4.</note> that (as the Church of
E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheſus was charged, ſo) you are become changelings, and haue forſaken
your firſt loue? And what ſhould I name in particular, that
ſtedfaſtneſſe in faith, modeſtie in words, that vprightneſſe in
actions, mercie in workes, that diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pline in manners, loue and vnitie among
brethren, which in the primitiue Church was the glorie of the firſt
Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans? Yea and brethren, I muſt tell you, that you did runne well,
and what ſhould turne you out of the way of holi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, that you ſhould
haue an euill heart to depart from the liuing God? This you know of a
ſuretie, that to him that ſtriueth and contendeth, to him is the kingdome
gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen. <hi>The kingdome of God ſuffereth violence, and the violent take it
by force. To him that ouercometh, to him will I giue the crowne of
life,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Math. 11.12. Reu. 2.17. Math. 24 13.</note> Reuel
2.17. And againe, <hi>He that endureth to the end, he</hi> (and he onely)
<hi>ſhall be ſaued.</hi> And of <hi>full holineſſe</hi> 
               <pb n="66" facs="tcp:17075:36"/>we haue thus farre heard and ſpoken. And now followeth
the meaſure thereof, viz. <hi>in the feare of God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>in the feare of God.]</hi> This laſt part of my text and
labour, ſets downe, 1. the meaſure of our holineſſe, viz. <hi>(in
feare,)</hi> and 2. the obiect of this feare, viz. <hi>God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>For the former, I finde by obſeruation generally three kinds of
feare, a naturall feare, a fooliſh feare, and a feare of God: the two former
I finde not in my text, neither will the time giue me leaue to ſeeke them
out. But for the laſt, I finde it generally to be of two forts: the feare of
God, it is either ſeruile or filiall: the obiect of the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer, is Gods
iudgement; but the ground of the latter, are the effects of his loue and
mercie: and both theſe in a dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferent maner, are the meaſure and
foundation of holineſſe. And looke what difference is betwixt a ſeruant
and a ſon, they feare to offend, the one for puniſhment, the other for
loue: ſo howſoeuer good men loue God, euen of zeale vnto his glorie, yet it
is not amiſſe to be reſtrained from ſinne euen for feare of iudgement.
It is beſt (ſaith <hi>Auguſtine)</hi> to be a ſonne, yet better to be a
ſeruant then an enemie. <hi>Si non potes propter amorem iuſtitiae, fac
propter timorem poenae.</hi> The affection of an enemie is hatred, of a
ſeruant, is the rod of puniſhment; but of a ſonne, is loue and reuerence.
And accordingly I find three ſorts of feare: the firſt of which is meerly
ſlauiſh, lumpiſh, vnprofitable and dogged kind of feare, full of hatred
and diuelliſh de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpite, and indeed the feare of diuels and reprobate
ſpirits, which findes no mercie becauſe it ſeekes no mercie. And the
diuels do thus beiecue and tremble.</p>
            <p>But there is a feare of Gods righteous iudgements, which euen in
good men hath a good effect; for it reſtrai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth from impietie. <hi>Et maxima
eſt poena timorem amiſiſſe poe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nae. Bernard. I conſidered my
wayes,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 119.59.</note> (ſaith <hi>Dauid) and
ſo I tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned my feete vnto thy teſtimonies.</hi> For who ſo conſidereth
his wayes, ſhall find his wants; and withall remembring the terrour of Gods
iudgements, and the neceſſitie of his iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice <pb n="67" facs="tcp:17075:36"/>to
puniſh, yea and to puniſh according to the nature of offence, it will daunt
and terrifie the heart of any from offending, if it be not paſt feeling. And
this is that which <hi>Auguſtine</hi> hath to like purpoſe: <hi>Atimore
tenera conſcientia, à tenera conſcientia bona vita, hinc decreſcit
timor ſeruitutis, at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>que inde dulceſcit Deus peccanti:</hi> and thus the
feare of Gods righteous iudgements is to good purpoſe; for it is a bridle to
reſtraine from finne, and a ſtep to beget the third, which is the filiall
feare of loue.</p>
            <p>But Saint <hi>Iohn</hi> ſaith, <hi>Perfect loue caſts out
feare,</hi> 1. Ioh. 4.18. viz. this ſeruile feare, and begets another, borne
of the free Spirit, Pſal. 51. viz. this filiall feare, the feare and
reuerence of a ſonne to a louing father. Of this the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet ſpeaketh,
<hi>There is mercie with thee, O Lord, therefore ſhalt thou be feared.</hi>
And this is that of which Saint <hi>Luke</hi> ſpeaketh, <hi>We muſt ſerue
God without feare,</hi> Luk. 1.<note place="margin">Luk. 1.74.</note> And Saint
<hi>Paul</hi> makes it more plaine, Rom. 8. not in the ſpirit of bondage for
feare of puniſhment, but in the ſpirit of adop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and freedome, euen of
zeale vnto his glorie. And this is the beſt and moſt excellent way of
feare, which I do take to be the principall aime and intendment of my text. And
ſo to bring this feare backe to my text, and my text home to your ſelues.
Firſt becauſe we muſt <hi>grow to full holineſſe in feare,</hi>
obſerue,</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Doctr. </seg>
               </label> All our holineſſe muſt be perfected
in feare. For as I haue formerly noted, the greateſt perfection of our
holi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe hath in it many imperfections. According to the meaſure and
proportion of this life, ſo is our holineſſe, and no otherwiſe: yea and
the leaſt part doth not conſiſt in this, to know and confeſſe our
wants. Saint <hi>Paul</hi> wil there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore haue vs to <hi>workeout our owne
ſaluation in feare and trem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bling:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Phil. 2.</note> and
Saint <hi>Peter,</hi> to <hi>Paſſe the time of our</hi> mortall
<hi>pilgri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage in feare.</hi> Our eſtate is neuer ſecure of danger; for
the Angels, though in heauen, yet thence did they fall.<note place="margin">Iude.
Gen. 3. Math. 4.</note> 
               <hi>Adam</hi> and <hi>Eue,</hi> though in Paradiſe,
yet there tempted and ouercome. Our Sauiour in the vaſte and wilde deſert,
yet <pb n="68" facs="tcp:17075:37"/>there the diuell finds him. And the Saints of God,
though in the boſome of the Church,<note place="margin">Pſal. 105.</note> yet
they haue had many foule ſlips and falls; and therefore our holineſſe
muſt be perfected in feare.</p>
            <p>Secondly, ſeeing that the feare of loue, and not of
pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment, is the trueſt meaſure of our perfection, obſerue,</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Note. </seg>
               </label> We muſt grow to full holineſſe, euen
of zeale to Gods glorie, and goodneſſe muſt be loued for it ſelfe.
<hi>oderunt peccare mali for midine poenae:</hi> To do well for feare of
puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, is but an aſſes vertue. And herein is the triall of a
perfect heart, if a man can ioy in holineſſe conſcionably, though it come
alone, yea though accompanied with many miſeries. Singular is the example of
<hi>Dauid</hi> to this purpoſe,<note place="margin">Pſal. 119 126.</note>
Pſalm. 119. <hi>It is time for thee (O Lord) to lay to thine hand, for men
haue deſtroyed thy law: therefore</hi> (ſaith he, euen for the loue and
zeale that I haue to holineſſe and Gods glorie, therefore I ſay) <hi>loue
I thy command: ments aboue gold:</hi> and <hi>all falſe wayes do I vtterly
abhorre.</hi> This is the point; our perfection conſiſts in this, if we can
be content to embrace holineſſe, euen for it ſelfe, and for reuerence to
our hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenly Father. By which it may appeare, that feare, and the feare of
loue, is the meaſure and perfection of our holi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe.</p>
            <p n="1">
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſon. </seg>1</label> 1. Becauſe of the
danger that may befall vs for want of this feare, viz. leſt hereby we fall
from our conſtancie, and ſo for want of perſeuerance do hazard our
ſaluation. The diuell is a cunning and diligent aduerſarie,<note place="margin">Luk. 11.24.</note> ready to take adnantage vpon euery occaſion;
and if he find the houſe ſwept and garniſhed, and no reſiſtance be
made, he en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treth in and dwelleth there, and <hi>the end of that man is worſe
then the beginning:</hi> and therefore we ought at all times and in all things
to <hi>walke circumspectly</hi> and in feare.<note place="margin">Eph. 5.15.</note>
            </p>
            <p n="2">
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> 2. For feare of giuing offence to others:
and by our halting or ſtanding ſtill, we wound the weake hands and feeeble
knees of the brethren, and ſo become partakers of their ſinnes.
<hi>Praeceptamonent, exempla mouent:</hi> yea know, <pb n="69" facs="tcp:17075:37"/>that
examples in ſinne do draw multitudes to offend; and therefore we ought to
feare our ſelues, euen for the good of others.</p>
            <p n="3">
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> 3. Leſt that by our ſecuritie and
ſtanding ſtill, the ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mie be comforted, and haue cauſe to blaſpheme;
and the Angels of God and the Spirit of God be grieued within vs; who as they
do reioyce for the conuerſion of a ſinner, ſo do they grieue at the falls
of the righteous.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe. </seg>
               </label> The vſe of the point is to teach vs to
beware of ſecuri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, and to let the feare of God euermore keepe the doores
of our hearts: the wants whereof doth breed in vs a num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of ſoule,
and doth much withſtand the ordinance of God for our ſaluation. For when
men come to this, that they are cold to holineſſe; if they heare, ſo it
is; if not, they feele no great want: if they receiue the Sacrament, they haue
no great delight or ioy; or if they for beare, they feele no grieuance: and for
other exerciſes of religion, they can be content to do them for ceremonious
cuſtome, but not for conſcience and feeling. Such a ſecure and
careleſſe e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtate as this, doth ſhew them to lie in ſome groſſe
ſin pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently, or elſe are in danger to fall into ſome great
tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſion, or ſome grieuous puniſhment. But all the paths of the
Lord are hedged about with feare, that we ſhould not forget nor for ſake
the Lord at any time. Beleeue in God we cannot alwayes, and to reioyce is not
alwayes preſent: faith is ſometime faint, loue is little, ioy is ſicke,
hope is dead, and ſeeling fallen aſleepe; but the feare of God, in a godly
iealouſie ouer our owne wayes, is the meanes to recouer all againe. Our
ſanctification is but in part. He that thinkes that he ſtands, let him take
heed leſt he fall: and <hi>Bleſſed is the man that feareth alwayes.</hi>
Surely (brethren) it is a good thing through godly feare euer to get victorie
of out infirmities, before they come to be ioyned with the ſinnes of the
world, to the griefe of the godly, the reproch of the wicked, the trouble of
our owne conſciences, or the hazard of Gods glorie. Thus <pb n="70" facs="tcp:17075:38"/>
               <hi>the feare of God is the beginning of wiſedome,</hi> Prou.1. yea
and the perfection of holineſſe is the feare of the Lord. heare the end of
all: <hi>Feare God, and keepe his commandements.</hi> It is the Alpha and Omega
of our holineſſe, the meaſure and foundation of the ſame: and
<hi>Bleſſed is the man that fea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth the Lord,</hi> Pſal. 112.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Of God]</hi> My text hath at laſt brought me to the end of
our iourney, euen to God the Lord, who alone is to be feared. And ſeeing it
is now high time to leaue you, here I will leaue you, for I cannot leaue you
better then with God. Conſider therefore a little the height of his
Maieſtie, the brightneſſe of his glorie, the perfection of his
good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, the ſtrength of his power, the excellency of his wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome,
the eternitie of his being, the holineſſe of his truth, the
ſweetneſſe of his mercie, the bleſſedneſſe of his pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence, in
whoſe ſight there is length of dayes, and in his preſence is fulneſſe
of ioy for euermore. Let his name be had in honour, <hi>from the riſing of
the Sunne to the going downe thereof.</hi> Againe, <hi>Oh Lord of hoaſts, how
excellent is thy name in all the world!</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Againe, God is the feare of his Saints. For the ſtrength of
Iſrael, is a dreadfull God, clothed with vnſpeakable ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſtie as with a
garment; and the ſplendor of his glorie is ten thouſand times more bright
then the Sunne in his greateſt beautie: yea the beholding of his face is
preſent death to a mortall man. The Angels tremble, the heauens melt away,
the mountaines ſmoke, the ſea is dried vp, and Iordan driuen backe, and the
earth doth totter vpon the foundations at the ſight thereof. The voice of the
Lord is a glorious voice, and hath the preheminence, <hi>The voice of the Lord
bringeth mightie things to paſſe.</hi> Heare, and feare, and tremble before
the Lord your God, ye men of Iſrael.</p>
            <p>In concluſion therefore, ſeeing we know that one and onely
God, euer to be worſhipped and feared, whoſe au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoritie doth command, and
power execute, and proui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence gouerne vs and all things; let vs (as
<hi>Henoch</hi> walked <pb n="71" facs="tcp:17075:38"/>with <hi>God</hi>) ſo paſſe
the time of our mortall pilgrimage in feare and holineſſe, as if we walked
in his preſence, whoſe eye ſeeth all, and whoſe eare heareth all;
alwayes remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bring that his all-ſeeing eye, and all-hearing eare ſhall
bring you and me, and vs all to iudgement. In the feare of God therefore let vs
begin and ſo end all endeuours, to <hi>cleanſe our ſelues from all
filthineſſe of the fleſh and ſpirit, and grow vp to full
holineſſe,</hi> that at the appearance of the Sonne of God to iudge the
ends of the earth, we may be found faithfull ſeruants: and as we haue dealt
truly in a little, ſo he may then make vs rulers ouer much, through the
riches of his grace, who hath freely and formerly beloued vs, not for our owne
ſake, but becauſe himſelfe is loue, and takes delight in his owne
goodneſſe. To which God be aſcribed all goodneſſe, and glory, and
mercy, and power, both now and for euer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>more. Amen, Amen.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:17075:39"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
